<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the excellencie of a christian man, and how he may be knowen. Written in French by Master Peter de la Place, one of the Kings counsel, and chiefe president of his court of aides in Paris. Whereunto is adioyned a briefe description of the life and death of the said authour, to the end that euerie one may knowe what he was. Translated into English by L. Tomson</title>
            <title>Traité de l'excellence de l'homme chrestien et manière de cognoistre. English</title>
            <author>La Place, Pierre de, 1520-1572.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05093</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106746</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842456</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842456</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7109</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05093)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7109)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 473:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the excellencie of a christian man, and how he may be knowen. Written in French by Master Peter de la Place, one of the Kings counsel, and chiefe president of his court of aides in Paris. Whereunto is adioyned a briefe description of the life and death of the said authour, to the end that euerie one may knowe what he was. Translated into English by L. Tomson</title>
                  <title>Traité de l'excellence de l'homme chrestien et manière de cognoistre. English</title>
                  <author>La Place, Pierre de, 1520-1572.</author>
                  <author>Tomson, Laurence, 1539-1608.</author>
                  <author>Farnace, Pierre de. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[134] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barker, dwelling in Paules Churchyard at the signe of the Tygers head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1576]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>A translation, by Laurence Tomson, of: La Place, Pierre de.  Traité de l'excellence de l'homme chrestien et manière de cognoistre.</note>
                  <note>Includes, with caption title: A briefe collection of the chiefest points of the lyfe of Master Peter de la Place, whyle he liued counseller to the French King, and chief president in his court of Aydes, at paris: set forth by P. De Farnace.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the excellencie of a christian man.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: *(-*1) [par.] A-F G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; title page stained, affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7109:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7109:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE of the Excellencie of a <hi>Chriſtian man, and how he may be knowen.</hi> Written in French by Maſter Peter de La Place, <hi>one of the Kings Counſel, and chiefe Preſident of his Court of Aides in Paris.</hi> WHEREVNTO IS ADIOYNED A BRIEFE deſcription of the life and death of the ſaid Authour, to the end that euerie one may knowe what he was. Tranſlated into Engliſh by L. TOMSON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MATTH. V.</bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed are they which ſuffer perſecution for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes ſake: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Chriſtopher Barkar, dwelling in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Churchyard at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Tyg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:7109:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7109:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull <hi>Miſtres Vrſula Walſingham, grace</hi> mercie and peace from God the Father <hi>and from the Lord Ieſus</hi> CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording as your Worſhips pleaſure was, I haue peruſed this booke, and as wynde and weather would ſerue for paſſage, haue brought it out of France into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: The cauſe of your liking, can not be miſliked of any: and the iudgement of the right honourable my Maſter, may ſtande as moſt grounded in trueth and iuſtice, whereby he ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced him not onely to bee of the Religion of Chriſt, but alſo truely a religious Chriſtian. For ſurely, if I be not deceiued in iudgement, who ſo ſhal reade this booke, ſhal finde there was a Chriſt in the man, &amp; ſuch a Chriſt, as made him in deede a Chriſtian, not for a daye or two, not for fayre and calme weather onely, but from the firſt beginning of his entrance into the knowledge of God, to his very laſt breth, in moſt ſharpe and ſtormie tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtes, as witneſſeth his happy and bleſſed mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, in that moſt horrible ſlaughter of the Sainctes of God, on Barthelmewes daye in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris that wicked murdereſſe of Gods people, againſt whome their innocent blood crieth to God for vengeance againſt the daye of wrath. As he felt, ſo he wrote, and his feeling was with ſuch ſpirituall vnderſtanding, as that we may well ſee, hee was
<pb facs="tcp:7109:3"/>one of them of whome hee wrote, and by ſo well knowing himſelfe to his euerlaſting comfort, gaue vs a waye to knowe our ſelues for the ioyous aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our ſaluation. The greateſt comfort we haue, is to knowe that we are of the citie of God, and who ſo would honour vs the moſt, could not better perfourme it to our liking, then to aſſure vs we are the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Father, brought into that honour and dignitie, by Chriſt that died for vs, and gaue himſelfe for vs, and in whome we dwell, and he in vs, if we deceiue not our ſelues. As for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort we might reape, by being made me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and not beaſtes, though it be great, &amp; God is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore greatly to be magnified, yet conſidering what God did for vs, &amp; what we haue done againſt him, where he ſet vs by grace, and where we finde our ſelues through ſinne and rebellion, we haue cauſe rather to ſorowe, then to ioye, of heauines then of comfort: and in that reſpect, the verieſt varlet &amp; caitif that goeth vpon the earth hath as muche to triumphe in, as hath the beſt man of God, the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt child of our heauenly Father. For they are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as well as we, made to the image of God as well as we, haue as great light in them of natural reaſon &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, as we, witnes the Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that neuer knewe God, no worſe ſinners in Adam the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we, but we as bad as they, both of vs for our ſinne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt him in that man Adam iuſtly blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, iuſtly condemned. This the blind wyſe Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher did not ſee, and this the obſtinate Pelagian Papiſt at this day will not acknowledge, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they bothe lift vp their heeles againſt God, haue wicked thoughtes, and ſpeake blaſphemous wordes againſt heauen, and againſt their owne
<pb facs="tcp:7109:3"/>ſaluation. And becauſe this prerogatiue ouer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, but equalitie of and in mankinde, had not that in it, that might in deede comfort the heart of man, but rather caſt him down, his minde and purpoſe was to lay forth the other to vs, which is proper to vs, I ſay proper to vs, that are of the houſhold of faith, of the common wealth of Iſrael, citizens of heauen, felow heires with Chriſt, the children of God: and I ſay proper, becauſe the Heathen and Barbarians, be they neuer ſo wyſe, the Pelagians and Papiſtes, be they neuer ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly deuoute, haue neither part nor por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in it. And this is the preeminence, not to be called, but to be a Chriſtian, which whoſoeuer fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in himſelfe with a right feeling of true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which neither of the two before named hath (for the one fighteth againſt the name of Chriſt, the other can not abide to heare of any certaine perſuaſion &amp; aſſurance of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, that it is beloued of God, and that God is without doubt our Father,) hath the greateſt preemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that man can haue vpon earth, and the greateſt ioye and comfort that can be felt by man. All of vs at this day, in this part of the world, do ioye in this name, Chriſtian, and it is taken for the greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour that can be done to man, to ſaye he is no Chriſtian: And yet ſure it is, that euery man is not a Chriſtian, that is called a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euery man is not a Chriſtian that is Chriſtened, not euery one that ſayth Lord Lord, ſhal enter into the Kingdom of heauen, no more then euery one that was cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, was a true Iewe, or all that deſcended of the race of Abraham, were true children to Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham. There was amongeſt them Iſmael, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted
<pb facs="tcp:7109:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>his brother, and yet was he circumciſed, there was Eſau, whom the Lord hated, and yet was he circumciſed: So are there heretikes amongſt vs, Chriſtened, and yet not Chriſtians, for neither the cutting of of a piece of ſkinne in them, did make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true Iſraelites, neither dipping in a litell water, maketh theſe true Chriſtians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both of theſe ſtandeth in the ſpirit, not in the letter, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worke by grace and that of God, not in the outwarde worke of man. So that he that hath this honorable name, to be called a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath more cauſe to tremble then to reioyce, vnleſſe he haue a ſure teſtimonie both within and without, that he is in deede a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for the abuſe of Gods name can auaile man nothing at all, nay it furthereth and increaſeth his condemnation, as great credite committed to a ſeruant, and abuſed by that ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, procureth greater diſpleaſure. Howe we ſhal come to the knowledge of this preeminence and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, which is in vs, this booke ſheweth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo plainely and ſhortely ſet forth, I will not ſtande here to make any diſcourſe of it vnto your worſhip, onely I moſt humbly beſeche you to reade the booke it ſelfe, and there ſhall you finde it ſo well layd forth, as ſhalbe to your contentment and comfort. I could very willingly haue bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to haue entred ſomewhat into the matter, but I feare I ſhould haue ouerſlipped my ſelf, for I muſt needes confeſſe of my ſelfe, and to the glorie of GOD, I ſpeake it, that I can eaſelier enter into it, then come forth, ſo great comfort I receiue of the doctrine, which is the chiefeſt part of the ioye of my ſaluation. Were it not that I had good aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>and feeling of theſe markes whiche hee ſetteth downe, and are in deede the true mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of our ſaluation, both in vs and to vs, that we are ſaued, I ſhould deſpayre rather then hope, and bende my ſelfe wholly againſt God, then euer bee ſubiect or ſubmit my ſelfe to GOD. And therefore ſo oft as euer I enter into conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the wicked doctrines, whiche the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate and condemned Church of Antichriſt, giueth out and teacheth, I finde none ſo deteſtable as this poynt, that laboureth to take away from vs all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of Gods loue towarde vs, and of our moſte ſure and certaine redemption by the blood of Chriſt. They call it a preſumptuous doctrine, a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate doctrine, a doctrine that leadeth man to all kinde of diſſolutenes, an enemie to godlynes of lyfe and deuotion, a furtherer of all ſenſualitie, all luſt, all wickednes and rebellion agaynſt GOD. Though we are taught by the Scripture, that none can beleeue but ſuch as are appointed to ſaluation, and none can receyue Chriſt, and beleeue in his name, but they which haue this prerogatiue giuen them, to be ſonnes of God: though the Apoſtle ſay, Knowe ye not that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you: and agayne, The Temple of God is holy, which Temple you are: though Chriſt him ſelfe ſaye, Reioyce that your names are written in the booke of lyfe: and, Of thoſe whom my Father hath giuen me, I will not leeſe one: yet ceaſe they not agaynſt ſo manifeſt trueths of the Spirit of God, &amp; witnes of the Sonne of God, yea and euident ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God him ſelfe, to diſgorge their blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies tending to the ſubuerſion of ſoules, becauſe they enuie at other mens ſaluation, not paſſing, as
<pb facs="tcp:7109:5"/>ſeemeth by their doctrine, for their owne, though I iudge them not. Is it a preſumption for a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man to ſay as Chriſt hath commaunded vs and taught vs to ſay, Our Father which art in heauen? Or may I ſay, Our father, in doubt, whether he be ſo or no? No man can call God his Father, but in fayth, and fayth is nothing but an vndoubted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that we are beloued of God in Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued as children, becauſe he gaue his Sonne for vs, becauſe he the righteous, dyed for me the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, whereby as he became a ſinner, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him ſelfe in my place, ſo doo I become righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in that that God ſetteth me in his place: And becauſe our condition and ſtate is ſuch with God, Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour willed vs in praying, to pray thus, Our Father. For if this grounde go not before, we are lyers in ſo praying, Nay we blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme him in ſo praying, for he will not be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Father of the reprobate, no more then he will accept the ſacrifice of the wicked, whereof he ſayeth by his Prophet, that it is an abomination to him, for our prayers are ſacrifices, and if they be the prayers of his children, then are they ſweete ſmelling ſacrifices: but if they be the prayers of the wicked and reprobate, then are they an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lord. Do we not euery one of vs, in the Confeſſion of our fayth, ſay, I beleeue in God the Father? what do we lye, when we ſay ſo? Or muſt we doubt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſay ſo? Wel this is the doctrine of the enemies of God the Papiſtes, who ſay, it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption for any man to ſay that he is ſaued. Then I ſay, it is preſumption for any man to ſaye, that he is the childe of God: then is it preſumption for any man to ſaye, that God is our Father: then is it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption
<pb facs="tcp:7109:5"/>for any man to ſay that he is a Chriſtian: then is it preſumption for any man to ſay in a good and true faith, I beleeue in God. And ſo by this meanes ſhal the whole Catholike Church be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for charging vs to ſay ſo: then is Chriſt a lier, and a maſter of hereſies in teaching vs to pray ſo: then do we all wickedly to call and profeſſe our ſelues Chriſtians with ſuch confidence as we doo. And ſeeing their profeſſion and doctrine is ſo, that no man can aſſuredly ſaye that God is his Father, let them ſet it downe in flattermes, as they meane it, and let the ſtyle of the confeſſion of fayth, and the Lords prayer go as their doctrine is, after this ſorte, I doubt in God the Father almightie, I doubt in Ieſus Chriſt, I doubt in the holy Ghoſt, and If thou which art in heauen be our Father, halowed be thy name, and ſo forth. What a diueliſh doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is this? &amp; yet it is the doctrine of the church of Rome: what a deſperate doctrine is it? and yet it is the doctrine that we muſt confeſſe to be true, or els we be heretikes, we muſt be burned, wee muſt be condemned. Chriſtians I ſay, muſt be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, becauſe they ſay they are Chriſtians, for it is nothing els we ſay: we ſay we are the children of God, that is an hereſie, ſay they, and yet they will graunt vs to be Chriſtians. A ſtrange kinde of Chriſtian, that hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, and if we haue the Spirit of Chriſt, are we not Children? The Apoſtle teacheth vs all this: why then what is it els to ſay, we are Chriſtians, then to ſaye, we are the children of God? and is there any chylde of God that is not faued? Paul ſayeth, if ſonnes, then heires, heires of the kingdome, yea felowe heires with Chriſt. So then it is no more preſumption to
<pb facs="tcp:7109:6"/>ſay, I am ſaued, then to ſay I am the the childe of God: neyther any more preſumption to ſaye, I am the childe of God, then to ſaye, I am a Chriſtian. Oh but ſay they, this doctrine maketh men deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: for if they ſtand vpon thoſe termes once, that they are ſaued, they will care no more for good workes, they will abandon them ſelues to all kinde of ſinne. In deede they ſay, as they feele, for if thei felt what it were to haue this perſuaſion &amp; grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, they would knowe, that as they are freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, ſo are they to liue in righteouſnes: The true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and chylde of GOD, is more fearefull to ſinne, becauſe he loueth God, and is beloued of God, then all the wicked haue for feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He knoweth and is perſwaded, that as he is dead with Chriſt, ſo muſt he riſe againe with Chriſt in newnes of life, to liue after the Spirit, not after the fleſhe, and that God hath prepared his wayes to walke in, which are good workes. If the liues of all men were looked into, it would eaſely appeare, where were the greateſt abundance of ſinne, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the true Chriſtian who is a witnes of the trueth of this doctrine, or in the enemie of trueth; which can not abyde this doctrine. And why can he not abyde this doctrine? becauſe he can not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde to heare of the adoption of God, howe God hath adopted and taken vs to be his ſonnes in Chriſt before the foundation of the world was lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And why ſo? Becauſe they go about to ſet vp their owne righteouſnes, and therefore will not be ſubiect to the righteouſnes of god. If we do wel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, and if we beleue, becauſe we were appointed to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it not our wel doing that maketh vs to be Gods children:
<pb facs="tcp:7109:6"/>then are we not appointed to ſaluation, becauſe we beleeue: then are al their merites gone, then is al their fat in the fyer. A Heathen, a Phariſe, and a Papiſt, is no bodie vnleſſe he may merite, vnleſſe God may be bound to him, and not he to God: he wil not take the kingdome of heauen of gift, he wil haue it of duetie, and that is no God a mercie to him. This is the very point of the matter, iudge nowe which is the preſumptuous doctrine, either the heatheniſh phariſaicall papiſtrie, or the trueth of the Goſpel. But as I ſayd, I can more eaſely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the matter, then get out of it, the groſſenes of their hereſie is ſo notorious and brutiſhe, the trueth of our doctrine is ſo plaine and riche, that I can not conteine my ſelfe, if I ſhould folow my ſelf, I will therefore ſurceaſe and leue your worſhip to the reading of the worke it ſelfe, which ſhalbe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to inſtruct you in the waye of this trueth, and arme you agaynſt the aſſaultes of Satan by theſe his inſtrumentes. The Lord by his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit worke thoſe two effectes in you, for this preſent, ſo true and comfortable doctrine: and further leade you into al trueth, as he is the God of trueth, that in the day of the Lord Ieſus, you may be founde to haue walked without ſtumbling in whatſoeuer he hath thought neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to reueile vnto you for your ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 15. Sept. 1576.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips humbly at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement L. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7109:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7109:7"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A briefe collection of the chiefeſt points of the lyfe of Maſter Peter de la Place, <hi>whyle he liued Counſeller</hi> to the <hi>French</hi> King, and chief Preſident <hi>in his Court of</hi> Aydes, <hi>at Paris: ſet forth by P. de Farnace.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough, to iudge aright of any worke, we haue to conſider ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what the thing is in it ſelf, then to ſtande much vpon the authour of it, becauſe, as truth is, the opinions wherwith we are before poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, whether they be with or againſt the perſons, ſtay vs from iudging ſyncerely of their doings: yet notwithſtanding it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable cuſtome, not onely to ſet mens names before their bookes, but alſo to ſet downe what men they were, to the ende the reader may be the better prepared to taſte of the fruict when he ſhal once vnderſtand what tree did beare it: for it is to be thought, that the fruict wilbe like the tree that bare it. And therefore, ſeeing this worke came to mine handes, I was ſo bold to put forth this ſhort, but yet moſte true diſcours of the lyfe and death of the worthie man that made it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwyſe thus minded, though this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb facs="tcp:7109:8"/>had not fallen out, that it were an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie to poſteritie to ſuffer diuers thinges lye buryed vnder ſilence which befell him in his lyfe tyme, and are woorthie perpetuall memorie.</p>
               <p>Therefore, to begime at his byrth, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Peter de la Place,</hi> an <hi>Angouleſmian</hi> borne, was ſo well trayned by in learning, euen from a chylde, that he onely of all his brethren reſolued with him ſelfe to followe the ſtudie of the Lawes, wherein he profited ſo marueylouſly, that before hee was two and twentie yeeres olde, he made a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie vpon the title of Actions: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame tyme began to be a common pleader in the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> where he gote himgreat commendation and prayſe for excellencie of witte and eloquence in pleading, and eſpeciadly for ſingular vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of conſcience. For which cauſe alſo, the deceaſed King <hi>Francis</hi> the great, did him this honour to chuſe him for his Aduocat and Autourney in his Court of <hi>Aydes</hi> in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> In which office he behaued him ſelfe ſo well, that no man is able to bereue him of this commendation, that he kept his handes continually cleane from briberie, and neuer dyd any thing againſt his office,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:8"/>either for vnbrideled ambition or couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. King Henrie the laſt, hauing ſufficient teſtimonie of his good and vpright bearing of himſelfe, in ſteade of continuing him in this office, choſe him amongeſt a number of other to be his Preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the ſaid Court of Aides. And whileſt he was in this office, it pleaſed God to call him to knowe him, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yere <hi>1554,</hi> after a ſtrange fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion.</p>
               <p>About twentie yeres before, whyleſt hee was a ſtudent at <hi>Poictiers,</hi> it pleaſed God to make him ſee Maſter <hi>Iohn Caluine,</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing then that way with the Archbyſhop of <hi>Tillet,</hi> whome he was content to heare ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king honourably of the knowledge of God in generall, but when hee ſpake of the pure ſeruice of God, he made aſtaye there, as one very zelous of that religion wherein he had bene carefully brought vp. Yet ſo it was, that euen from that daye, there remained ſome ſcruple in his conſcience, that it might well be, he might be deceiued, and that his mynde ran vpon oftentimes as he confeſſed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde: which was as you would ſaye, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiue to nouriſhe this litle ſeede, vntill it came to budde forth and ſpring, at ſuch time as God had appointed it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7109:9"/>
               <p>After this it fell out on a daye, that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at his doore, there came a certaine ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to him, by a wonderfull prouidence of God, whom he knewe not, but ſeeing him to be a man of ſome qualitie, and one that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted reliefe in his extreme pouertie, turned to hym very humbly, and made him a long diſcourſe in excellent Latin vpon the cauſe of his miſerie. And finding hym to be a man well qualified, cauſed him to come in euen into his ſtudie, to feele hym the better to the bottome at his leaſure. Then this poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as one ſent from God, began to diſcyfer out frankely vnto hym all the abuſes of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe Church, and to ſhewe hym the true and onely way to ſerue God. And after he had heard him patiently, he rewarded him, and prayed him notwithſtanding very earneſtly to come no more to him, ſo afraid he was of the fyers which were prepared againſt them which were ſuſpected the leſt that might be, for the doctrine of the Goſpel: as in deede this poore ſtranger, not long after, was tried in the fornace at Paris.</p>
               <p>But after this, <hi>Peter de la Place,</hi> left not tourning both the Scriptures and al the old fathers, euen to the very ſcholemen, to finde ſome meanes if it were poſſible, to take away
<pb facs="tcp:7109:9"/>this ſcruple which troubled his minde day &amp; night. By this meanes in ſhortſpace, God touched his heart, and opened his eyes, and cauſed him to behold the light of the Goſpel, in ſo much as after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of King Francis the ſecond, he declared him ſelfe openly to be of their number that made profeſſion of the reformed Religion. And about that time put forth a treatiſe concerning our Calling, to King Charles the ninth that dead is, and ſhortly after put forth an other treatiſe in printe, touching the right vſe of <hi>Moral Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie,</hi> with the doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>So that when the troubles encreaſed, for his owne ſafetie, hee departed from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, and withdrewe himſelfe to an houſe of his in <hi>Picardie:</hi> where all the tyme of the troubles hee gaue himſelfe wholly to the ſtudie of Diuinitie, as the onely and true Philoſophie, (ſayde hee) which is able to miniſter to man true ioye and comfort in his griefes and miſeries: and vſed oftentymes to exhorte his familie to the feare of God, and exerciſed them in prayers. And ſome part of his tyme alſo he gaue to write howe matters of Religion and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth paſſed, diuers pieces whereof, vnwares to him were imprinted, <hi>Anno 1565.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7109:10"/>
               <p>When theſe warres were ended, in the yere <hi>62,</hi> he went and preſented him ſelfe to the King, to purge him ſelfe of many falſe bruites which certaine euill willers had caſt out of him in the warre time: at what time, after that his Maieſtie was ſatiſfied with his anſweres for his defence, finding the late Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> that dead is, in the Court, he went and did his duetie to him: who, for his part, receiued him ſo courteouſly, that from that inſtant, he gaue him the charge, and made him ouerſeer of all his houſhold affaires, which he tooke in ſo good part, that in all matters that concerned his honour, he ſpared neither goods, nor children, nor him ſelfe, ſo carefull he was of his ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Fiue yeres after, when the troubles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan afreſhe, he withdrewe himſelfe againe, from Paris to the Caſtell of <hi>Ve</hi> in <hi>Valois,</hi> which belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged to his nephewes, by the right of <hi>Miſtres Ragonde Luillier</hi> his wyfe, to whom he was at that inſcant, tutor. During the time of theſe warres, he ſuffred great per ſecutions: but neither the loſſe of his office, nor the ſale of his moueable goodes, nor the ſeaſing vpon his vnmoueable, troubled or diſquieted him ſo much, as the diſcourteſies did which hee receiued at their handes, of
<pb facs="tcp:7109:10"/>whome he ought in courtieſie haue reaped great hope of helpe, as of them that were neareſt to him in blood, amongeſt all which, I can not let paſſe one vnſpoken of, who ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed him ſelf very barbarous and diſcourte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and is a Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeler of the Court, (howe be it I am content to concele his name) and did once not onely knowe the trueth of the Goſpel, but that more is, made open profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, but afterwardes forgat himſelfe ſo farre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he played as lewde a touch as might be with the ſaid <hi>La Place</hi> his kinſman. For whereas he profeſſed the religion, yea and that after the firſt troubles, perceiuing that God proued his children ſomwhat ſharpely, he reuolted by and by, and ſeeing himſelf in ſome danger by threates caſt out againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that had bene of the religion, to auoyde all ſuſpicion of grief that he might conceiue for his reuolte, or of deſire to returne to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of good men, he purpoſed with himſelf to commit ſome notorious acte, as he forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with performed it in ſlandering and giuing forth the worſt ſpeaches he coulde, againſt this <hi>Peter De la Place,</hi> taking this occaſion, which I will tell you, to make ſome ſhewe of his doing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter de la Place,</hi> was tutor to his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewes,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:11"/>which were childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this Counſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers wife, &amp; had, as I ſaid before, withdrawen himſelf to a certaine caſtel of theirs. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Counſeler ceaſed not by way of ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſlanderous requeſtes and ſupplications, to forge and put into the heads of the Court of parleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a thouſand lewde &amp; wicked prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes &amp; ſlanderous reproches: in ſo much as he cauſed this ſaid <hi>La Place,</hi> while he was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and knew nothing of theſe matters, not onely to bee diſcharged of the office of his tutorſhip, to his great reproche, but alſo gate forth a commiſſion to get hym poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſaide caſtel, and to arreſt the ſaid <hi>La Place.</hi> Which no doubt had bene executed in ſo vnhappy and trouble ſome a time, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what diligence he cauſed <hi>Tanchou</hi> &amp; his archers to make, as if they had gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> taking of ſome thief &amp; murderer: had not God raiſed vp a friend, who came a night before and tolde him of the whole matter. Whereupon though he were in a continual burning ague, yet he was conſtrained to ſaue himſelfe in the foreſt of <hi>Rez,</hi> which is hard ioyning vpon the Caſtell, where he light vpon a ſtranger, that tooke hym in, whereas this Counſeler not onely againſt all right of
<pb facs="tcp:7109:11"/>kindred, but alſo contrarie to all humanitie ſeaſed vpon his Caſtel, caſt out the children of the ſaid <hi>Place,</hi> and ſpoiled ſuch goodes as he had left there: and beſide all this barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous vnkindnes, ſent <hi>Tanchou</hi> and his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to purſue him. Who by this meanes was conſtrayned to remayne in the foreſt as a vagabond a good ſorte of dayes togither, vntill at lengthe the Lorde of <hi>Bouchauane</hi> ſhewed him this courtieſie, to take him ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſecretly into a litle chamber in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell of <hi>Couſſy,</hi> where hee was conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to remaine faſt ſhut vp, comforting him ſelfe in theſe his diſtreſſes and miſeries with the reading of the holy ſcriptures, at what time he gaue himſelfe to ſome deeper conſideration of the excellencie of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, and to wryte this lytle trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</p>
               <p>Afterwarde when it pleaſed GOD to giue his poore Churche ſome breathing time, he retourned home to his houſe, and though there were ſome reſiſtance made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hym by one that in the tyme of the warre, had enryched himſelfe with ſpoyle of his goods, yet hee reentred into the office of his Preſidentſhip, and executed in without any reproche, being honoured of all good
<pb facs="tcp:7109:12"/>men, and feared of the wycked, vntill this curſed <hi>S. Barthlemewes</hi> day, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>24.</hi> of Auguſt, the laſt day of a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of honeſt mens liues, yea and of the very chief &amp; flowres of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And amongeſt the reſt was this man <hi>De la Place</hi> moſt cruelly murdered, in maner as foloweth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>24.</hi> day about ſixe of the clocke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning, there came to his houſe one Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Michel by name, an harquebuſier of Charles the ninth, whom he was the better content to receiue into his houſe, becauſe he tooke him to bee one of the Kings Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhe garde, for many of them loued him very well, and offred their ſeruice to him often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. When this Captaine Michel was thus entred into his houſe, armed with an harquebouze on his ſhoulder, and a piſtol at his gyrdel, and a table napkin about his left arme in token he was one of the murderers, the firſt wordes he ſpake were theſe, that the Duke of <hi>Guyſe</hi> had by the Kings comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement ſlaine the <hi>Admiral,</hi> and many other noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the religion: and becauſe al the reſt of the <hi>Huguenots,</hi> of what qualitie ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they were, were appointed to be murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he was come to this Gentlemans houſe <hi>La Place,</hi> to deliuer him out of this calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
<pb facs="tcp:7109:12"/>But yet he would they ſhould ſhewe him all the gold and ſiluer in the houſe.</p>
               <p>Then this Gentleman <hi>de la Place,</hi> ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at the proudnes of this man, that being but one in the houſe, and amongeſt ten or twelue perſons, he durſt vſe ſuch wordes, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him if he knew where he was, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there were a King or no. To whom this Captaine anſwered with othes, that ſeeing it was ſo, he ſhould go with him to the King, and ſo he ſhould knowe his pleaſure. When this Gentleman <hi>la Place</hi> heard this, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douting that there was ſome great ſedition in the towne, ſlipped out at a backdoore, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to ſaue him ſelfe in ſome of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſes. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane ſeaſon moſt part of his ſeruants conueyed them ſelues away, and this Captaine hauing gotten about a thouſand crownes, as he was departing was requeſted by Miſtres <hi>Marets</hi> daughter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Gentleman to condict her &amp; Maſter <hi>Marets</hi> her huſbande, to ſome Catholiques houſe, their friend, which he did.</p>
               <p>After this, the ſayd <hi>la Place,</hi> hauing bin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed at three houſes, was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to come home to his owne, where he found his wyfe very deſolate, and tormenting her ſelfe very pitifully, both for feare leſt this Captaine
<pb facs="tcp:7109:13"/>would haue caſt her ſome in lawe and her danghter into the water, and alſo for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent daunger ſhe ſawe her poore huſbande and all her familie in. But this Gentleman <hi>la Place,</hi> ſtrengthened with the ſpirit of God, and with marueilous conſtancie rebuked his wyfe ſharpely, laying forth before her, howe paciently they had to receyue ſuch afflictions at Gods hands: and ſo when he had a litle diſcourſed vpon the promiſes that God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to his children, he put her in good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               <p>Afterward he commanded his men ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and mayde ſeruants that were left to be called in, &amp; as he vſed euery Sabbath day to make ſome kinde of exhortation to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, he gaue him ſelfe to prayer, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde began to reade a Chapter of Job, and Maſter <hi>Caluins</hi> ſermon vpon it, and made a ſhort diſcourſe vpon the iuſtice and mercie of God, who (ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he) as a good Father ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſeth his choſen people with diuers cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements, to the end they ſhould not ſtaye themſelues vpon worldly things. He ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them moreouer how neceſſarie afflictions are for the Chriſtians, and that neyther the world, nor the deuill are able to hurt vs fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then it ſtandeth with Gods good will
<pb facs="tcp:7109:13"/>and pleaſure to ſuffer them, and therefore we neede not feare their power which reacheth no further then to our bodies. And after this, he gaue him ſelfe to prayer agayne, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring him ſelf and al his familie to ſuffer al kinde of torments, yea &amp; death it ſelf, rather then to do any thing againſt Gods glorie.</p>
               <p>When he had ended his prayer, one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth and telleth him that Maſter <hi>Seneſcay</hi> Prouiſt of the towne houſe and a nomber of Archers were at his gates, and commanded them to open the gates in the Kings name, and ſayd that he was come to garde <hi>la Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> perſone, and to kepe his houſe from ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by the multitude: vpon this occaſion, this Gentleman <hi>la Place</hi> commanded the gate to be opened, and ſo he came in and told him what ſlaughter there was made of the <hi>Huguenots</hi> throughout all the towne, and that by the Kings commandement, adding theſe wordes amongſt the reſt in Latin, that there ſhould not one be left, that could piſſe againſt a wall. Notwithſtanding he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commandement from his Maieſtie to ſee there were no hurt done to him, but to bring him to the <hi>Louure,</hi> becauſe he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to be inſtructed by him of diuers mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters touching them of the Religion, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:7109:14"/>he had to deale in, and therfore that he ſhould make himſelfe ready to come to the King.</p>
               <p>This Gentleman <hi>la Place</hi> anſwered, that he would thinke him ſelf happy for euer, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he departed out of this worlde, he might finde the meanes to giue the King an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of all his doings and behauiour. But for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme, conſidering what horrible ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were committed all the towne ouer, it woulde be impoſſible for him to get to the <hi>Louure</hi> in ſafetie, without great and moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of his perſon, but he might wel aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his Maieſtie of his perſon, if it wold pleaſe him to leaue ſuch a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Archers in his houſe, as he ſhould thinke meete, vntil the furie of the people were a litle appeaſed. <hi>Seneſcay</hi> graunted him his requeſt, and left him one of his Lieutenants, called <hi>Toute voye,</hi> and foure of his Archers.</p>
               <p>Shortly after that <hi>Seneſcay</hi> was depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Preſident <hi>Charon</hi> then Prouiſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Marchants of <hi>Paris</hi> came to the houſe, and after he had talked a whyle with him in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, departed &amp; left him foure of the towne Archers beſide the Archers of <hi>Seneſcays</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie. All the day after and the night follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was beſtowed in ſtopping vp and ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the wayes into the houſe, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:7109:14"/>pebbles and ſtones vp into windowes, ſo that by this great and painefull watche there was ſome likelyhood, that theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers were placed in the houſe for the ſafetie of <hi>la Places</hi> perſon, and to preſerue his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that common miſerie that other felt, vntyl <hi>Seneſcay</hi> came backe the next day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing about two of the clocke in the after noone and ſhewed him, that he had expreſſe &amp; preciſe commaundement from the King, to bring him, without any further delay. This Gentleman <hi>la Place</hi> ſhewed him as before, what danger there was for him in the towne, ſeeing that the ſelf ſame morning, there was one of his neighbours houſes ſacked. Al this notwithſtanding <hi>Seneſcay</hi> was earneſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary, ſaying that it was a common vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Huguenots</hi> to proteſt great hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes, and ſay that they are the Kings moſt obedient ſeruants and ſubiects, but when it came to the point to obey the Kings co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, they ſhewed them ſelues very colde, and it ſeemed by them that they could in no wyſe brooke it. And as for the danger, he ſayde it was for him to go to the <hi>Louure, Seneſcay</hi> anſwered him, that he woulde giue him a Captayne of <hi>Paris,</hi> which ſhould be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wel knowen to al the people, to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb facs="tcp:7109:15"/>him. Whyle <hi>Seneſcay</hi> was thus talking with him, a Captaine of <hi>Paris,</hi> called <hi>Peſou,</hi> and one of the chiefeſt cutthrotes came into this Gentlemans <hi>la Place</hi> his chamber, and offred to conduct him. <hi>La Place</hi> refuſed him very earneſtly, ſaying to <hi>Seneſcay,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was one of the cruelleſt and wickedeſt men in all the towne, and therefore deſired him onely, ſeeing he could refuſe no longer to go to the King y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it would pleaſe him to go with him, whereto <hi>Seneſcay</hi> anſwered that by reaſon of other buſines he had to doe, he could not go with him aboue <hi>50.</hi> paſe.</p>
               <p>Whereuppon this Gentleman <hi>la Places</hi> wyfe, though ſhe be a Gentlewoman on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god hath beſtowed many graces &amp; bleſſings, yet notwithſtanding the great loue ſhe bare to her huſbande, cauſed her to fal downe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate before the ſayd <hi>Seneſcay</hi> and beſeeche him to accompanie her huſband. But with that, this Gentleman <hi>la Place,</hi> who neuer ſhewed any token of an heart caſt downe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to take vp his wyfe, &amp; reproue her, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her that it is not the arme of man which we muſt haue recourſe vnto, but to GOD alone. Afterward turning him ſelfe a ſide, he eſpied a croſſe of paper in his eldeſt ſonnes cappe, which he had of weakenes ſet there,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:15"/>thinking to ſaue him ſelfe by that meanes, whereupon he rebuked him ſharpely, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding him to take that marke of ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of his cappe, and laying foorth before him, that the true croſſe whiche we muſt beare, are tribulations and afflictions which GOD ſendeth vs, as moſte certaine pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and earneſt pennyes of that ioye and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life which he hathe prepared for his children. Then ſeeing him ſelfe earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſſed by the ſayde <hi>Seneſcay,</hi> to go to the King, reſoluing him felfe to dye the death whiche he ſawe prepared for him, tooke his cloke, embraced his wyfe, and deſired her aboue all things to haue the honour &amp; feare of God before her eyes, and ſo departed with a moſt cheerefull countenance.</p>
               <p>Nowe when he was almoſt come to the ſtreete called <hi>la Verrerie,</hi> ouer agaynſt the Cocke ſtreete, certaine murderers that wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for him with their daggers ready drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aboue three houres, ſlewe him lyke a ſilly lambe in the middeſt of ten or twelue of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſcays</hi> archers which guyded him, and his houſe was ſacked the ſpace of fiue or ſixe dayes togyther. The bodie of this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman <hi>la Place,</hi> whoſe ſoule was receyued into heauen, was carryed into a ſtable, at
<pb facs="tcp:7109:16"/>the towne houſe, where his face was coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with dong, and the next day after in the morning was caſt into the riuer.</p>
               <p>Thus this great and excellent martyr of the Lord, whyleſt he obeyed the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, in ſtede of Iuſtice whiche he ſought, found death by the way, whiche was to him a beginning of the true lyfe: and on the contrarie ſide, both to them, from whom ſo vniuſt, agaynſt all Gods lawe and mans lawe, and ſo cruel and barbarous and more then brutiſhe commandementes, proceeded, and alſo to the executers of ſuch iniquities, cruelties, barbarities, and brutiſhnes, a moſt certaine beginning and entrance to an horrible iudgement that hangeth ouer their heades, &amp; ouer their poſteritie, though it ſeeme long before it come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7109:16"/>
               <head>Of the excellencie of a Chriſtian man, and the way to knowe him.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y intent and purpoſe</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to intreat of the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of a Chriſtian man,<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to al men.</note> I meane not in any wyſe to ſtande to diſcourſe vpon the excellencie of mankind wherein we do all communicate, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſtate of man ſurmounteth the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all other creatures: a reaſon which moued the Philoſophers to recommend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs ſo diligently the knowledge of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, according to the old prouerbe giuen by Oracle, and framed by them to this purpoſe to cauſe vs not onely to keepe our ſelues within the boundes of modeſtie and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes, and to teache vs the weakenes of our nature, but alſo to leade vs to the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our noblenes and dignitie, beginning by the vewe of the building and workeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of this world, as of Heauen, the Sunne, the Moone, and the Starres: and ſo from them to other creatures and liuing things of diuers ſortes, ſetting out Man, as the moſt excellent piece of worke of all, and the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb facs="tcp:7109:17"/>wrought thing emongeſt all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, on whome it pleaſed God to beſtow moſt plentifully, and to enriche with that, which Heauen and earth, and all other his creatures had but ſmall portions of, who was therefore called a Little worlde, and a miracle amongeſt all creatures, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the workemanſhip of his bodie, the iointes, the proportion, the beautie and vſe of it with his members, his head aboue all his other partes, his eyes looking vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to beholde from whence he came: and againe, the quickenes of his wit, his diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vpon the heauens and the earth, and the ſecretes of nature, his memorie whereby he comprehendeth ſo many things &amp; digeſteth them, compareth things paſſed with things to come: Moreouer his reaſon which as they imagine is placed as Queene &amp; Miſtreſſe in the wit in the higheſt ſeate of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to gouerne the wil of man, and to frame all his deliberations by the compaſſe of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre to a Chriſtian.</note>I meane not, I ſaye, in any wyſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate of this kinde of worthines: but min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to paſſe further, I purpoſe with my ſelfe to ſpeake of an other kinde of excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, which is propre and peculiar to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb facs="tcp:7109:17"/>man, which farre ſurmounteth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all compariſon in all kinde of preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and preeminence the former, be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo highly commended and ſet out by them which profeſſed themſelues wiſe men, and were therefore reputed and taken for the wyſeſt amongeſt other. Which men notwithſtanding or wyſe Philoſophers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried away with an ouerweening and blynde loue of them ſelues, ouerſhot them ſelues ſo farre, as to ſaye, that Man is able, by reaſon of ſuch powers as he hath in him,<note place="margin">A fooliſh prayſe of the powers and vertues that are in man.</note> and by his owne ſtrength, to diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene good and euill, and commaunde his luſtes, and that he hathe it in him to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne him ſelfe, not onely for the framing of this earthly lyfe, but alſo to leade him to Godwarde, and to the attaynement of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting bliſſe and ioye. Moreouer, that as touching Life, he hath it by the gyfte of God, but as for Liuing well, he hath it of him ſelfe, and the goodnes that is in man, man getteth it of him ſelfe, in ſo much as no wiſe and diſcrete man, ſayeth <hi>Cicero,</hi> euer gaue God any thankes for it, becauſe, ſaieth he, we are commended for our vertue, and we brag &amp; boaſt our ſelues of it: which we could not do, if it were the gift of God, &amp; came not of
<pb facs="tcp:7109:18"/>our ſelues: adding moreouer, that the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of al the world is this, that as for world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commodities, we haue to craue them a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, but as for wiſedome, euery man hath to ſeeke it within him ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Mainteyning and publiſhing this falſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that what ſoeuer we do by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct and guyde of nature, it can not be but well done, and if man could followe that rightly, which he hath in him of nature, he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doo amiſſe. And many other ſuche foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and vayne ſayings, which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (a thing more to be ſorowed at) they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> make profeſſion to be our inſtructors in holy writte, do marueilouſly embrace: who by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering them ſelues to be caried away more then reaſon would they ſhould, by this kinde of heatheniſhe wiſedome, are fallen into the ſelf ſame errour, and haue aſcribed to man I knowe not what kinde of integritie and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes both in his reaſon, and will, in ſo much that euen they amongſt them which thought to ſpeake more ſoberly and modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then the reſt, as <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> and certeine other, haue made ſuch a parting of ſtakes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God &amp; man, that while they confeſſe on the one ſide, that we can do nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods helpe, they mainteine on the other
<pb facs="tcp:7109:18"/>ſide, that vnleſſe we bring ſome thing of our ſelues, the grace of God can not helpe vs: for as they ſay, all the matter lyeth not in Gods helpe, but we muſt caſt in our rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning alſo: yea, and that it is in vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and in God to make an ende, holding this for an vndoubted trueth, that GOD hath giuen man power to doe well and to do euill, both when, and as him liſteth, and that he is at his own choyſe, to take of them, which he will.</p>
               <p>This I ſay, to ſhewe, howe with all the light of vnderſtanding and vprightnes of reaſon,<note place="margin">A blindnes, euen in the knowledge of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie that is in man.</note> (whereunto they aſcribe the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raintie of the whole man, making it as it were a Monarche and Emperour) man is blinded and daſeled with the knowledge of the excellencie, which he laboureth in vaine to finde in him ſelfe by the knowledge of his powers, and beholding all things that are within him. And ſo conſequently how much they abuſe them ſelues, which thinke there is no better way to moue and perſwade men to frame their liues accordingly as they ought, then to put them in remembrance what goodly and precious things they haue in them, for thereby they wilbe moued to make ſome accompt of them ſelues, and be
<pb facs="tcp:7109:19"/>more carefull to keepe them ſelues in their place and degree, ſhunning ſinne, and follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing righteouſnes: ſeeing that all this can ſerue to no other purpoſe, but to puffe him vp with vayne glorie &amp; ouerweening of him ſelfe, and cauſe him to weary him ſelfe in conceyuing a good opinion of him ſelfe, which will not further him the worth of a pinne, and then to vndertake ſuche things, as he ſhall neuer be able to compaſſe, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the reache of reaſon, nor by accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing in deede what he intended. For the knowledge of a mans ſelfe, according to the rule of trueth,<note place="margin">The true knowledge of a mans ſelfe.</note> ſtandeth properly in this, that man weye with him ſelf the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtate and condition whereinto we are fallen through the fall of Adam, to the ende that hauing a right feeling of it as wee ought, all vaine glorie and preſumption may be beaten downe in vs, with a deepe conſideration of the loſſe of our vprightnes, and in ſteade thereof, of a corruption and fall from all goodnes, which is come vpon vs by reaſon of the corruption of our nature, Satan hauing ſo faſt footing in al the parts of our ſoule, that euery one of vs in him ſelf (as <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi> ſayeth) is become a Deuil, enemie to God, and accurſed on all ſides,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:19"/>to the ende that being liuely touched by this meanes with the feeling of our vanitie and frowardnes, we may be moued to come out of our ſelues, as voyde and deſtitute of all goodnes, and ſeeke our excellencie, worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and noblenes ſomewhere els, yea and be moued to ſighe, and in ſighing to breathe after it with great deſire to recouer the ſame.</p>
               <p>Whereby it appeareth howe groſſely they were deceyued &amp; abuſed which thought to fynde the worthines of man within man him ſelfe, and in that that is of man.<note place="margin">Their errour, whiche haue ſoght mans excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lencie in that which is of man.</note> The cauſe of their errour is this, that the ſecret of their deſtruction and fall, which came by our firſt fathers fault, &amp; wherein they would nedes ſeeke a fayre and ſound buylding, was not reueyled vnto them. Whereby it came to paſſe, that through pryde which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of them ſelues for that ſmal remnant of light that remayned of the firſt beginning which was included in our nature, (whiche they call a little portion of the Godhead) they ſpake ſo boldely and preſumptuouſly of that which they knewe not, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man for that whiche in deede is not in him, and wherfore he is not in any wyſe to be
<pb facs="tcp:7109:20"/>commended. And ſeeing the caſe ſtandeth ſo, that though man be fallen into a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtate through the fall of Adam, and the image of God in him be marred and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably deformed, yet he hath ſome ſparkes left, whereby there remayneth in him ſome darke light and perceyuerance of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of his nature, that is to ſaye, of that vprightnes wherewith the firſte man was beautified and made noble, ſo that the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of ſinne was not able to doe ſo muche, as vtterly to deface the image of GOD in vs, but that there remained al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſome litle trace of it, thereby it came to paſſe, that men pricked and awakened with the feeling of the reliques of their firſte dignitie and excellencie (inwrapped notwithſtanding in darkenes, and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a peruerſe and preſumptuous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to haue ſomewhat of their owne, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning within them) were eaſily moued to prayſe and commende the excellencie of theyr nature: which fooliſhe deſire being once preſented to the vnderſtanding and brayne of each ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the ſame deceyuer that would needes perſwade our fathers to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like to God, there is not one of vs that
<pb facs="tcp:7109:20"/>hath not a roote of pryde deepely planted within his heart.</p>
               <p>Not that I meane to denie, but that litle vnderſtanding that man hath in him euen of nature for the maintenance of this preſent life, and that diſcretion of good and euill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graued in his heart, yea &amp; that piece of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God which he hath naturally in him, is not out of doubt excellent, in that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from God: but I ſaye, that all theſe thinges are defiled in man, euen as wyne that hath receiued infection by the vnſauery taſte of the veſſel, wherinto it was put,<note place="margin">All the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of man, as of man, is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the grace of his ſauour and goodnes is gone, and hathe gotten beſide a bitter and vnwholſome taſte. Becauſe, the iudgement and diſcretion which he hath left to diſcerne and make his choyſe of thinges, is partly imperfect and full of confuſion, and all the witte he hathe, becommeth vayne, as alſo his will is tempeſtuouſly caried and full of phrenſies accordingly as man is wholy ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried awaie with ſinne, and to be ſhorte, his vnderſtanding, and perceyuerance which he hath of GOD is nothing els, but verie horrible welſpring of errours, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not onely by the idolatries and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions which he inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth, but alſo herein, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7109:21"/>wheras the heauens keepe their natural mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, &amp; the waters their accuſtomed courſe, the byrdes make their neſtes, and the plantes bring forth fruit eche one in his due time, &amp; to be ſhort, no creature ſubiect to man faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his worke, man indued with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, iudgement, diſcours and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, is he that onely erreth, and erreth in ſuch ſort, that in the whole world, there is no fault, no diſorder &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion, but on his part. So that, to ſpeake truely, there remaineth not one droppe of vprightnes in his whole nature, ſo farre is he from that excellencie, wherof I meane to ſpeake, by reaſon of the corruption that is in him, as euery man will freely confeſſe, that can and doth rightly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the heauie ſight of his decaie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon nature of man is not capable of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of a Chriſtian.</note>Wherefore ſeeing that this our nature, which is common to all men liuing, is not capable of that excellencie whereof I ſpeake, we muſt nedes ſay, that that man of whom I ſpeake, is tranſformed into an other new and more excellent nature, whereupon God hath beſtowed a ſingular &amp; wonderfull ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which farre paſſeth and ſurmounteth al that is in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as in dede it can not be found, nor be confeſſed to procede from any, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, yea from the Lord and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt: by whom his good pleaſure was to
<pb facs="tcp:7109:21"/>reſtore al mankind, towards whom though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoueraignecreat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; maker of al things ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly his fatherly fauour diuers &amp; ſundry ways, yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, vntil he ſhew himſelf to man a reſtorer in the perſon of his only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne, their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience reproueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, &amp; maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perceiue that by reaſon of their filthines they are wel worthy to be caſt away as wretched men &amp; caitifs, &amp; cannot be taken &amp; acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted for his worke eſtabliſhed in them. In which worke is only &amp; truely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie wherof I meane to ſpeake, which is a worke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> farre paſſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man, as it wil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare more plainly hereafter, of which man when <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">The won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful work of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in a Chriſtian.</note> he ſaieth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> might &amp; power, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie power of God is plentifully ſhewed in him, becauſe he ſetteth forth in him, after a wonderful ſort his infinite vertue, according to the vnſpeakeable goodnes, grace, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, which he beareth to a Chriſtian man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of God which appea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth in a Chriſtian.</note>And that it is ſo, to ſhew it more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, our heauenly father not content that he brought a Chriſtian into the world, of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and that he made him not an oxe or an aſſe, which he might haue done, or a dogge, or a catte, or any other more bite and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect creature, but a man, that is to ſaye, a
<pb facs="tcp:7109:22"/>ſingular and perfect piece of workemanſhip, and that he made the world &amp; beautified the heauens and the earth with a perfect abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, varietie, and beautie of all things, to lodge him in it, as it were in a great &amp; ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous palace, well and richely furniſhed with all thinges neceſſarie, not content I ſay, with al this, &amp; moroeouer, that he had forgotten his vnthankeful and deteſtable infidelitie and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie, where he deſerued to be caſt of, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued for euer of all his bleſſinges: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding it pleaſed him, of a certein more then fatherly loue, and ſpeciall fauour which he bore him, not onely euen from his birth day, and from the firſt howre that he brought him out into this world, but euen from his mothers wombe, yea, and before he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, yea, and that more is, before the world was made (as he predeſtined him to him ſelf from euerlaſting) to elect and chuſe him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt an infinite million of men, to marke him &amp; ſet him apart, to exempt him from the common ſtate and condition of al other men, that is to ſay, from euerlaſting condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and deſtruction which was prepared for him as wel as for euery other man, to reſerue him for him ſelfe, to adopt, and regenerate him in the hope of life to an incorruptible inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:7109:22"/>kept in ſtore in heauen, to be reueiled to his elect at that day when all thinges ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, and to ſhewe in him the richeſſe of his glorie, as in a veſſell of mercie prepared to ſaluation.</p>
               <p>All the cauſe of this excellent prerogatiue and dignitie,<note place="margin">The cauſe of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of a Chriſtian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſteth in the onely good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God.</note> is not as we ſee to be ſought any where els, but in the ſingular grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, whom it pleaſed without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regarde or conſideration of any thing without him ſelfe, foreſeing the faulte and condition of mankinde, of his good pleaſure to haue mercie vpon ſome, to ſet them in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as veſſels of his mercie, and leaue the reſt in their iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, giuing grace to ſome which was not due to them, and rendring to the reſt that puniſhment that was due to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being in his power to giue to one part that which they deſerued not, ſo ſetting forth his grace: and not to giue it to all, thereby ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what al had deſerued without further be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing like mercie on all: for he made all things, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, for his owne ſake: yea, the wicked man to the day of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, according to the decree of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good pleaſure of his wil, which onely is the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine and high rule of iuſtice that iudgeth al the world: his wayes, which are mercie and
<pb facs="tcp:7109:23"/>trueth being incomprehenſible, as whereby he ſo worketh, that they which obteine mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie at his handes, haue nothing but his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to boaſt of, and they that are left in their condemnation, haue nothing to gaineſay the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of trueth as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> guiltie, nor ought wherewith to pleade againſt him, in ſo much as on the one ſide, to ſhewe forth his wrath, and make his mightie power knowen, he through great patience and meekenes bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with the veſſels of wrath prepared to deſtruction, &amp; on the other ſide, ſetteth out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> richeſſe of his glory towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he choſe by his grace, whom he prepared to glorie.</p>
               <p>For ſo it is, as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſheweth it at large,<note place="margin">Of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall councel of God, tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching man.</note> where he ſpeaketh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> predeſtination of God, that when God had reſolued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him ſelf, to buyld the Monarchie of this world &amp; al that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in it, &amp; forſawe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the firſt man ſhould fal wittingly and willingly into death, being pliable to good &amp; euill, hauing not that giuen him to continue &amp; ſtande ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily in that ſtate wherin he was placed: yea and that al mortal creatures ſhould be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of his fall, &amp; ſubiect vnto it, hauing ſo appointed it by his incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible counſel and wiſdom, which hath a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge of all thinges ioyned with it, as
<pb facs="tcp:7109:23"/>alſo his mightie power which gouerneth all thinges by his hande, and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding minded to haue a litle re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nant, euen as you would ſay, an handful of men taken out of ſuch a great multitude, to ſerue for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiſe of the glorie of his grace, he choſe &amp; ſet apart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the multitude, one man amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt many, which ſhould be in his time ordeined to be conceiued of the ſeede of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and ſhould be borne of a virgin, to wit, Ieſus Chriſt, (finding nothing in all the ſeede of <hi>Adam</hi> worthy his election, and ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue and excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie) in whom alſo as in the head, he choſe to be members as it were of his bodie, ſuch as it pleaſed him freely of his grace to appoint before hand &amp; receiue to life: and by the ſelfe ſame man, to ioyne them vnto him ſelfe, and allie them ſo togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they ſhould neuer be ſeuered, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing foreſeene a great while before that in <hi>Adam,</hi> there ſhould come good of euill, and knew moſt vndoubtedly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it belonged to his almighty goodnes to turne good into euill, rather then to ſuffer that there ſhould be no euill, and ſo accordingly diſpoſed the life of men and Angels, as that he would thereby ſhewe firſt what free wil was able to do, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of his grace could do, hauing
<pb facs="tcp:7109:24"/>ſhut all vnder ſinne, that al might haue nede of grace.</p>
               <p>And therfore as the excellencie which I aſcribe to a Chriſtian, and proceedeth from this grace appeareth fully and abundantly in Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of a Chriſtian appeareth fully in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</note> ſo is it powred out vpon his members according to the meaſure of euery one, by which grace man was made a Chriſtian when he firſt began to belieue, as our ſauiour was made Chriſt according to the fleſhe,<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of a Chriſtian procedeth of that ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which is in Chriſt.</note> when he firſt began to be man. And therefore was hee called Chriſt, and the other by his meanes, Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes flowing from the chiefe fountaine: for ſo had the Almightie purpoſed in him ſelfe to gather them vnto him,<note place="margin">All the elect are gathered together in Chriſt.</note> by the blood of the Croſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, at the fulnes of time appointed, finding them miſerably ſtrayed and ſcattred amongſt the other, and ſet them in their right ſtate: whiche is, to cleaue continually to him, being knit and coupled together with him in a true &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite vnitie, by engraffing them into the bodie of his ſonne. Who for that cauſe are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led elect or choſen through the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God, to make a difference betweene them and the other which were not kept in the ſaid vnitie, but forſaken by a ſecret repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation
<pb facs="tcp:7109:24"/>in the ſecret counſel of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The cauſe and matter of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of a Chriſtian is wholy to be referred to the loue and goodnes of God by Chriſt from euerlaſting.</note>So that, whether we meane the cauſe, or the matter it ſelfe of the excellencie of a Chriſtian man, ſo farre I am either from ſeeking or ſetting the ſaid excellencie of a Chriſtian, in man him ſelfe, as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers doe, that I meane not to aſcribe it to any thing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, but to that headſpring of all graces, benefites, and bleſſings, that is to ſaye, to the euerlaſting loue and gracious goodnes of God by Ieſus Chriſt, in whom God choſe his elect before the foundation of the world, to adopt them according to the purpoſe of his will, and made them agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his welbeloued ſonne, who was by him appointed head ouer them, which by him &amp; through him, and no otherwiſe, are reſtored and ſetled in his grace, and made his heires to enioye his kingdome, where as before they were a curſed raſe of <hi>Adam,</hi> and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of hel fyre. for the Father loueth none, but in his Sonne,<note place="margin">The vaiting and ioyning together of a Chriſtian with Chriſt</note> and vouchſafeth none his inheritance, vnleſſe he firſt ioyne them to his ſonne by a ſecret bond &amp; vnitie, cauſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of the head to deſcende into the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as the ſappe of the roote of the tree goeth into the graffe that is imped into it, in ſo much as this ſpirituall bond and knot
<pb facs="tcp:7109:25"/>belongeth not only to the ſoule, but alſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, &amp; ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, fleſh of his fleſh, &amp; bones of his bones, yea eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo farre forth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they beare his name &amp; perſon before God, and he rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected in their perſons, then in his own. To be ſhort, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as naturally the only beholding of the face of man moueth vs to loue him and al his parts, though if we ſhould vew his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers apart we might happily find ſomewhat to miſlike vs, &amp; bring vs out of taſt, ſo fareth it likewiſe with the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who is a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ieſus Chriſte, being conſidered in Chriſts face &amp; perſon, which when God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth in his elect imprinted as it were in them by repairing of his image in them, loueth and cheriſheth them, as perſons with whom he is well pleaſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of a Chriſtian doth wel ap peare in the felowſhip which he hath with Chriſt.</note>So that to ſpeake in few words, it is this felowſhip which they haue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are called, both by the communion of one ſelf ſame ſpirit, &amp; one ſelf ſame nature which is both in them and him) wherein the excellencie of a Chriſtian man conſiſteth and appeareth very euidently, in that he is ſet in the higheſt degree of honour being made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childe of God, by Ieſus Chriſt taking vpon him that that was proper to man to be made
<pb facs="tcp:7109:25"/>man as he was, and to make him felow with him ſelfe in that that was proper to him ſelf, by making him the ſonne of God. For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce commeth this holy brotherhood, whiche he teacheth vs, ſaying, I go to my father &amp; your father, to my God &amp; your God. Being not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed (as the Apoſtle ſaith) notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the great oddes that is betwixt him &amp; vs, to abaſe him ſelf ſo far as to cal vs Brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had put of al his infirmitie, vs, I ſay, which are not otherwyſe worthy to be vnder his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.<note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man farre paſſeth all other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> Herein ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appeareth to be a loft, not onely aboue al other liuing creatures by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his owne nature, as the Philoſophers ſay, but alſo aboue all other men by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence which thoſe Philoſophers knew not at all, whereby he ſurmounteth the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the firſt man, taking him in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt perfection he euer had, becauſe the grace of God is farre more ſetled and ſure in the regeneration of the faithfull, then it was in the firſt ſtate of man, that beyng greater which we haue recouered in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">That which the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recouereth in Chriſt, is greater then that which he loſt in Adam.</note> then that which we loſt in <hi>Adam.</hi> For <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had grace giuen hym to continue in goodnes, if he had would, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtian it is giuen to haue a will, and in hauing a
<pb facs="tcp:7109:26"/>will he ouercommeth his luſtes. So that <hi>Adam</hi> might if he would, but he had no wil, that he might: and the Chriſtian hath both will and might giuen him. ſo that the firſt libertie was giuen to <hi>Adam,</hi> that he might abſteine from ſinne and not die: but that that is giuen to the Chriſtian, (the pledges wherof we haue here, and looke for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in heauen) ſtandeth in this, that he can neither ſinne nor die, becauſe the elect are vnſeparably knit with Ieſus Chriſte their head, which bond maketh them ſtrong and ſtedfaſt, to cleaue to God for euer.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, this excellencie of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man mounteth ſo high, that it ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth the excellencie of the verie An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, in this reſpecte that the euerlaſting Sonne of God vnited him ſelfe to mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not the nature of Angels, minding to perfit and accompliſhe in it, the wonderful worke of our redemption: and afterwarde hauing glorified it with immortalitie, by his reſurrection, hee ſet it in his heauenly kingdome aboue all principalities and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly powers in all honour and glorie: ſo that the Chriſtian man being partaker of the fleſhe of Chriſt which is carried vp and reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth on hygh, hath part alſo of the ſame king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:7109:26"/>and glorie. And though the Angels, as touching their naturall eſſence, are counted more excellent then man, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, becauſe they haue no head of their kind and nature, the Sonne of God, euen accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſhe, ſurmounteth them in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and noblenes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The chiefe excellencie of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de like vnto God.</note>To this purpoſe, <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſtians, thought it not inough to ſay, that they are a choſen generation, an holy race, a peculiar people to ſet forth the great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of God, and a Royall Prieſthode, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to Ieſus Chriſt, to offre ſacrifices, not for the remiſſion of ſinnes (For that office is throughly accompliſhed by Chriſt Ieſus his onely ſacrifice, the force whereof remaineth for euer) but ſacrifices of prayſe, and thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, and calling vpon the name of God, which are the calues of our lippes, and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of beneuolence, &amp; imparting our goods with the poore: he thought it not enough, I ſay, to giue them all theſe ſo great and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable titles, but goeth on further and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, they are made partakers of the diuine nature, which is ſo excellent a condition, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of man is not able to imagine or wiſhe an higher. For in dede, what can a man deſire more, then to become like to God? ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely
<pb facs="tcp:7109:27"/>the ſpirit of man is not ſufficient &amp; able to comprehend the greatnes of this grace, &amp; how it might be that God ſhould vouchſafe to honour man ſo highly, as to make him a God as it were, if we may ſo ſay, by making him partaker of his diuine immortalitie and bleſſed glorie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man is made perfect in Chriſt.</note>And therfore <hi>S. Paul</hi> writing to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> and ſpeaking to them as to Chriſtians, ſaith that they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleat in Chriſt, when he had ſaid a litle before, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fulnes of the godhead dwelleth bodily in him, ſhewing therby, that this perfect eſſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Godhead which is in Ieſus Chriſt, did auaile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that, that they receiued thereby their perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo. And in that that God is wholy in him, is to the ende that when they once poſſeſſe him, they might obteine ſuch a perfection in him, as none of vs is able to atteine vnto by all the wit &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding we haue. Yea ſo farre forth, that this knot &amp; bond is ſuch an one, that Ieſus Chriſt who worketh all in al, vouchſafeth the Chriſtian thus much honour,<note place="margin">The wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vniting of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian with Chriſt.</note> that he cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth him ſelf after aſort imperfect, if he be not ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> witneſſeth, ſaying, that the Church is the filling vp of the bodie of Chriſt. And therefore there is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile, if the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> rauiſhed with great admiration of this ſo wonderfull
<pb facs="tcp:7109:27"/>goodnes &amp; loue of God towards mankinde, and being as it were rauiſhed &amp; beſides him ſelfe cried and ſaide, Lorde what is man that thou ſo regardedſt him? that is to ſay, that of thy gracious goodnes thou haſt made hym ſo excellent a creature? For if he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider &amp; ſeeke his firſt beginning from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he came, where ſhal he finde it but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> durt &amp; duſt of the earth? if he marke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of his abode, he ſhall finde him ſelfe ſcrauling here vpon the earth below: if he looke to his end, he ſhall ſee that his bodie ſhalbe meate for wormes. And yet notwithſtanding, ſaith he, thou haſt ſo highly honoured this poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Man, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angels ſerue him, as if he were a God. for thou haſt made him a litle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to God, &amp; haſt crowned him with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and honour, and placed hym ruler ouer the workes of thine handes, and haſt put all things in ſubiection vnder his feete: As if he would ſaye, what occaſion did durt giue thee, that of it thou ſhouldeſt make a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to thine image and likenes, whom thou wouldeſt make Lord and Maſter of all the worlde? and put in ſubiection vnder his feete what ſo euer is vnder the compaſſe of heauen? ſpeaking of the man that is reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7109:28"/>
               <p>For in deede it is he onely, and none but he amongeſt all liuing things that is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lord of the world,<note place="margin">Only the Chriſtian is Lord of the world.</note> by recouering that inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in Chriſt, which was before loſt in <hi>Adam</hi> who was at the beginning made heire and Lord of all Gods bleſſings, but was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes diſpoſſeſſed of them through his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſtion, and diſobedience, ſo that all his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie hath no other intereſt nor title, in the bleſſings of this world, then theeues &amp; rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers haue, whiche take awaye other mens goods, the Chriſtian onely except, to whome of right belongeth the vſe of all things, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, whether it be the world, or life, or death, or things preſent, or things to come, al things, in a word, are his, becauſe they were made for his profit.<note place="margin">All things are profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Chriſtian, yea, euen ſin it ſelfe.</note> And there is nothing, but God maketh it ſerue, &amp; turneth it to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, in ſo much that by a ſpeciall diſpenſation of his prouidence, he cauſeth that the very ſinnes them ſelues which man committeth, turne rather to his ſaluation then to his hurt, in that that by them he humbleth them, and maketh them better taught,<note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man is from euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting in the heart of god</note> and more adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. To be ſhort, this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a creature y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> from euerlaſting was in Gods heart through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is Gods treaſure.</note> &amp; therfore a thing ſo riche &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may well be called Gods treaſure.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7109:28"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">He deſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of a Chriſtian.</note>But ſeeing I haue begun to dilate this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of a Chriſtian man by the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting counſell of GOD, whiche he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and appoynted within him ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the worlde was, according to his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious goodnes fully ſet forth in IESUS Chriſt to al them whom he hath coupled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther with him. It ſhall be good nowe to come lower, and to treat of the matter, as it were by deſcent from heauen to earth, and to ſhew this excellencie more particularly in a Chriſtian,<note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is a creature whom the world kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not.</note> beginning at his regeneration and ſo going on from point to point, to ſhewe howe miraculouſly he is formed, nouriſhed &amp; brought vp to rype age: what maners he is of, what his life is, and what his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation, to ſet him out after this ſort in his coulours &amp; markes as he is. For in dede he is a newe creature, whom the world knoweth not, and an hidden treaſure in a vile and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble veſſell, hard to knowe, if he be not well marked out &amp; ſet forth with liuely colours. And leſt in diſcourſing of it, we fal headlong into the ſame errour, which the wiſe fooles of the world fal into in their diſcourſes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his excellencie, it ſhal not be amiſſe, if at the entrie of the matter, I warne euery man to beware he preſume not ſo much of him ſelf,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:29"/>as to imagine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath ought of his owne,<note place="margin">Man may bring no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his owne to make him a Chriſtian.</note> as though he had in him ſelfe any piece of a cauſe, meane, or ayde to ſet forwarde this worke.</p>
               <p>Therefore, as I ſayde before, that we haue not to ſeeke the cauſe or ground worke, or matter of this excellencie any where els,<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of a Chriſtian procedeth from Gods election, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing that is in man.</note> but in the mere grace of God according to his euerlaſting prouidence: ſo ſay I againe, to ſhut out all worthines of man, that al the goodnes &amp; vertue that may poſſibly be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in man, proceedeth from the fruict of Gods election: and therefore to be a Chriſtian, that is to ſay, the beſt of all creatures, proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth wholy from the gift of our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in that that whatſoeuer he hath giuen to Chriſt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to Chriſt, and in that that no one whit of the worlde belongeth to the Creature, were it not that the grace of god plucketh a fewe out of deſtruction, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſhould haue periſhed, the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left in that deſtruction, whereunto it is moſte iuſtly appoynted. And for this cauſe Ieſus Chriſt proteſteth, that he prayeth the Father for them onely whome the Father hath giuen him. For in deede, the grace of God findeth no cauſe in any man, why hee ſhould be good vnto him, but man receiueth
<pb facs="tcp:7109:29"/>all of his mercy, becauſe it is Gods worke onely to ſaue his, and for that ende and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to make them fit and meete to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his inheritance. And for a man to imagine any pretence for man in this caſe, it were as muche as if he ſhoulde go about to make him his owne maker. And if we doe wel to giue God al the prayſe for the direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this our corruptible life, howe may we be ſo bolde to aſcribe that vnto our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, which is without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon a thouſand tymes better? to wit, the lyfe that periſheth not, but remayneth for euer, ſeeing it is a great deale eaſier to make vs men, then by our owne induſtrie and vertue to be rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate into a farre more excellent nature.</p>
               <p>Whereupon S. Paul, to take away all preſumptuous opinion of mans brayne in this behalfe, ſayeth, That it is neyther in the willer, nor in the runner, that is to ſay, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in merite, nor worthines, nor induſtrie; nor will, nor helpe, or any meanes that man can worke, but in the onely goodnes of our Lord and Maſter, who doeth all things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the counſel of his good will, not according to our workes, but according to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> purpoſe of his grace, which was giuen vs by Ieſus Chriſte before the worlde was. And
<pb facs="tcp:7109:30"/>this ought of a trueth content vs and ſuffice vs for all reaſon that may be brought: for to go about to ſearche out any other, what were it els, but to open a gappe for raſhe and heady fellowes to demande in like ſorte a reaſon of al his workes, why he beſtoweth his graces more vpon ſome, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon other, as to beginne with the brute beaſtes, why God made them not reaſonable creatures: and why he made not a woman, a Man: and why he made not the ignorant, weake and poore man, a wyſe, ſtronge, and rich man: and as touching the elect them ſelues, why they are not the ſame that their head is, why there is ſo great oddes betweene them, why they are ſo vncleane, and he very cleannes it ſelfe, and ſo in ſumme, why he beſtoweth not his giftes, as well vpon this man, as vppon that man.</p>
               <p>And yet my meaning is not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God hath no reaſon for making ſuch a difference betwene his creatures as he hath done: but becauſe that reaſon is hidden within his ſecret coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, I ſay, it muſt ſuffiſe vs for good and all, that his will was ſo, and ſay with <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> that faithfull ignorance is better then raſhe knowledge: yea that ſuch ignorance is learned, and the deſire to knowe more, is a
<pb facs="tcp:7109:30"/>kinde of madnes. Therefore when we ſee that ſome haue this honour done them, that they are made Chriſtians as well as other, though we ſee no euident cauſe why it ſhould be ſo, we muſt learne to ſtand in admiration of the deepenes and profoundenes of Gods iudgement, whiche we may in no wyſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of: and therefore euery one of vs hath to content him ſelfe to knowe, that to be a Chriſtian, is the workemanſhip,<note place="margin">To be a Chriſtian, is the onely worke of God.</note> as S. Paul ſayeth, and creature of God, created in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and that God hath bleſſed him with all ſpiritual bleſſings in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly things in him, as he choſe him in him before the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the worlde, being predeſtined of God to adopt him to him ſelfe, according to the good pleaſure of his will to the prayſe of his grace, which he hath powred out moſte plentifully vpon him, in all wyſedome and vnderſtanding, and to whom he hath giuen to knowe the ſecret of his will, according to his euerlaſting decree which he purpoſed in himſelf, being moued thereunto by no other meanes, then of him ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note>So then to come to the regeneration of a Chriſtian, and to ſpeake of the order that is holden therin, Firſt of al we may not dreame of any ſuch generation as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> made,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:31"/>who thought that as ſoone as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bodies were dead, the ſoules went into other bodies: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may we dreame of any naturall genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or power of man, whereby this man ſhould be made after this ſorte: for this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is not wrought by a corruptible &amp; vncleane ſeede, as the firſt was whereof we are all partakers, which can engender no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but corruption, nothing can be borne of fleſhe but fleſhe, whoſe ende is death and deſtruction: but by an other and ſecond ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is ſpiritual, made of an holy &amp; vncorruptible ſeede, whiche is the worde of God preached, whereby thei that are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſaluation, are called and begotten to him. For in deede there is no other differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betweene Predeſtination, and Calling, but this, that predeſtination is a preparatiue of that, whereof the calling is the effect and the accompliſhment: and yet my meaning is not, that this generation is made by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of one ſimple worde vttered by the voyce of man which ſoundeth onely in the eares, which God vſeth as his meanes and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to call all men indifferently to him: (for many are called, ſayeth Chriſt, but fewe are choſen, and it were to ſet a mortall man to much on cockhorſe to ſaye that his voyce
<pb facs="tcp:7109:31"/>were ſo pearcing of it ſelf as to work a rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſoule of man) but I ſay, it is by an other inward calling of God, by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the outward which is wrought by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which inwarde calling maketh it ſelfe heard within, by drawing the hart vnto it, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueth the witnes of the euerlaſting grace, and without which, the voice of man could be but a bare ſounde that vaniſheth away in the ayre, and a literall preaching &amp; dead without any fruit, the ſeede time being of litle valew, vnleſſe the increaſe be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by vertue of that life which is reſerued onely for them whiche were appoynted vnto it from the beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, according to the purpoſe of God, and no purpoſe of theirs: to whom onely it is giuen to knowe the ſecrets of the kingdome of heauen, all other men being ſhut out and left to their owne nature, whereby they are deafe and blinde, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyued and borne ſuch of the vncleane ſeede of their parentes, hauing beſide a darkened vnderſtanding whiche can not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehende the myſteries of God: for his worde is couered and hidden to them, ſo that they can no more perceyue the glorious and bright ſhining light of it, then blinde men ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the light of the Sunne: for no man can come to Chriſte, vnleſſe he haue a ſpeciall grace
<pb facs="tcp:7109:32"/>who thought that as ſoone as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies were dead, the ſoules went into other bodies: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may we dreame of any naturall genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or power of man, whereby this man ſhould be made after this ſorte: for this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is not wrought by a corruptible &amp; vncleane feede, as the firſt was whereof we are all partakers, which can engender no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but corruption, nothing can be borne of fleſhe but fleſhe, whoſe ende is death and deſtruction: but by an other and ſecond ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is ſpiritual, made of an holy &amp; vncorruptible ſeede, whiche is the worde of God preached, whereby thei that are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſaluation, are called and begotten to him. For in deede there is no other differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betweene Predeſtination, and Calling, but this, that predeſtination is a preparatine of that, whereof the calling is the effect and the accompliſhment: and yet my meaning is not, that this generation is made by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of one ſimple worde vttered by the voyce of man which ſoundeth onely in the eares, which God vſeth as his meanes and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to call all men indifferently to him: (for many are called, ſayeth Chriſt, but fewe are choſen, and it were to ſet a mortall man to much on cockhorſe to ſaye that his voyce
<pb facs="tcp:7109:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7109:33"/>giuen him from aboue.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How a man becommeth a Chriſtian.</note>Nowe as touching the way that our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father taketh in framing a Chriſtian man, this it is, he firſt determined in him ſelf to make the world and all things to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and men eſpecially, to ſhewe to one ſorte of them which are predeſtinate to ſaluation, his mercie, and to the other ſorte, his iuſtice: And to this effect he appoynted for an onely and ſole Mediatour, Ieſus Chriſt his onely begotten Sonne, of one ſelfe ſame ſubſtance with him ſelfe, euen God euerlaſting, to the ende that by him being made man, &amp; the two natures vnited and ioyned togither in one in him, all corruption of mankinde might be purged, and all righteouſnes fully accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in him for all, as one able ynough to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyne the iudgement of God, and woorthie ynough to appeaſe his wrath by the offering vp of himſelfe, the iuſt dying for the vniuſt, and to ſanctifie all his elect, aboliſhing theyr ſinne in them by the communication of his death, and quickening them by his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. To be ſhort, he determined with him ſelfe to giue them his ſonne, and in him what ſoeuer is requiſite for their ſaluation, as alſo to giue them to him, and ſo to make them Chriſtians, by ingraffing them into Chriſt:
<pb facs="tcp:7109:33"/>which euerlaſting purpoſe and decree, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued alſo to reueile vnto them, when they ſhould not thinke of it, cauſing him ſelfe to be founde, as the Prophete ſayeth, of them, which inquired not after him, &amp; at that time, that they walke after the courſe and faſhion of this worlde, euen as Satan woulde haue them, and proceedeth in it after this ſort.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to awake them out of the dead ſtepe of ſinne wherinto they are fallen, he pricketh them with the ſharpenes of his Lawe, and laying a nomber of examples of his Iuſtice before them, driueth them into a feare, not minding to beate them downe into deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but to make them turne their faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Mediatour, in whome they may finde ſome place of refuge. And to this end, he layeth before them in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion his grace and fatherly goodnes by the preaching of his Goſpel, He teacheth them, he maketh them apt to receyue inſtruction, aſſureth them of their election, ſummoneth them to his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly inheritance, ſtretcheth out his hande vnto them to bring them thyther, yea and draweth them vnto him, faſhioneth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> new eares, lighteneth their eyes, changeth theyr ſtonie heart into a fleſhy heart, openeth their vnderſtanding, reneweth their ſenſes, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:7109:34"/>and maketh them fit to ſauour and taſte his worde, which he ſoweth, and cauſeth it to budde and bring foorth fruit in them, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them fit for his election. To be ſhort, when he hath once formed Chriſt in them, he decketh and enricheth them with many gyftes and graces, and whereas they were farre of from him, he maketh them drawe neare to him, of ſtrangers he maketh them houſebirds, of wolues ſheepe flocking togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnder the great paſtour of ſoules: of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, fleſhly, earthly, and deueliſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them heauenly, ſpiritual, angellike and diuine: and by this meanes tranſlateth them from the kingdome of darkenes, into the kingdome of light, tranſporteth them from death to life, and bringeth them into his own houſholde. To be ſhort, hauing thus ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed them into the body of his Sonne, he ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and allieth him ſelfe to them, he maketh him ſelfe one with them, maketh them his children and heyres, partakers of his immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie and glorie, and all this he worketh by the inward vertue of his holy Ghoſt, &amp; with an other maner of efficacie then by reſtoring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reliques of free will, as ſome popiſh mates vſe to ſpeake, ſeeing that all the remainder that man hath of this free will, ſerueth to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:7109:34"/>els but to ſinne willingly, to flie from God, to hate him, and to haue no wil to heare him, nor beleeue in him, nor acknowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his bleſſings: and that more is, to think vpon nothing but vpon ſinne, and not to haue ſo much as one good thought.</p>
               <p>Which wonderfull order <hi>S. Bernard</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, cryeth out and ſayeth, Beholde an high and marueilous counſell, which hath bene publiſhed to vs. God knoweth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are his, and what he knewe, he hath ſhewed to men: he receyueth none to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of this myſterie and hidden thing, but ſuche as he hath predeſtined. And addeth moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, The mercie of God from euerlaſting to euerlaſting on them that feare him: from euerlaſting, becauſe of his predeſtination: to euerlaſting, becauſe of the bleſſednes which they looke for, the one hath no beginning, &amp; the other hath no end. <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi> alſo ſaith in lyke ſort, Is not this a kinde of ſchole, far from the ſenſe of the fleſhe, wherein the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the ſcholemaſter that teacheth vs to come to him, and the Sonne of God is the worde whereby he teacheth, and whiche en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth by the eare euen to the heart; where is alſo the Spirit of the Father and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne, who teacheth alſo iointly with them, and not
<pb facs="tcp:7109:35"/>a part, for the workes of the Trinitie are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable, ſo that, if we ſee nombers come to the Sonne, it is by him that maketh many to beleue in Chriſt. But where &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery man hath heard &amp; bene taught by the Father, we ſee it not, becauſe this grace is hidden, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret &amp; heauenly, wrought by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> renewing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt, powred out plentifully vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the power of God in the generation of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note>And truely, it is a marueylous generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which maketh man a new creature, not that he receyueth an other ſoule, or an other body in ſubſtance, but in qualitie, by repayring the Image of God in him, by an inward renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the whole nature, that was corrupted: yea it is a worke which ſetteth out vnto vs no leſſe vertue and power of God, then that whereby Ieſus Chriſt was rayſed from the dead, and placed at the right hand of God his Father. To be ſhort, it is done by the word, as by the ordinarie inſtrument whiche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs partakers of Chriſt, and frameth the Chriſtian man, ſo that vnleſſe the doore of our hearing be opened by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preaching of the Goſpell, the worde can not enter into the heart, and the preaching is wrought by the voyce of man aſſiſted by the inward vertue of the holy Ghoſt, which man muſt be ſent by a ſpecial grace of God, to declare vnto vs, that
<pb facs="tcp:7109:35"/>this ſpecial grace is according to his electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is according to his euerlaſting coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, determined according to the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his will, which onely is iuſt and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. And ſo conſequently both the calling, and other effects that follow, flowe from the euerlaſting Election, as brookes and ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes doo from their fountaines and ſprings.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a Chriſtian is from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion.</note>Therefore, ſeeing this man is not begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten eyther of fleſh or blood, as other are, but of God, it is not for naught that I ſayde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that he is ſuch a creature, as the worlde knoweth not. For in deede his beginning is not from hence beneath from the earth, but from aboue from heauen, as alſo his chiefeſt conuerſation &amp; abyding place is there where he hath God for his Father: and here the church for his mother,<note place="margin">The Father and Mother of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note> but yet in deede hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly: Mother, becauſe ſhe hath her begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from that grace, that is aboue, &amp; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner becauſe ſhe is gardien and keper of the ſeede of that life that periſheth not, by which ſeede ſhe conceyueth and bringeth forth this man, and when ſhe hath brought him forth, ſhe nourceth him with the ſeaſoned milke of vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">The nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of a Chriſtian.</note> that being nouriſhed by it, he may growe vp to ſaluation. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſhee foſtereth him with ſtronge and
<pb facs="tcp:7109:36"/>ſubſtantiall meate, vntyll he come to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect age, that is, to the attainement of the latter ende of fayth. Euen as the natural ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, conceyued of naturall ſeede is nouriſhed with blood in his mothers wombe, and fed afterwarde with milke whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is once borne, as all creatures are nouriſhed with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they are inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred, euen ſo the regenerate man, conceyued &amp; begotten of the incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible ſeede of the worde of God, is nouriſhed and foſtered by it, receyuing the ſame ſimply and purely, without any mixture and hotch poch of any other mans inuention with it.</p>
               <p>For as there is no food more holſome the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foode of the worde of God,<note place="margin">The nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of the pure worde of God is wholſome.</note> if it be recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſyncerely as it is, ſo there is none more noyſome and hurtful, when it is marred with mixture of other things mingled with it, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the falſe doctrine of men: And therefore God ſpeaking to his Church by the mouth of his Prophet Eſai, ſayth after this forte, My ſpirit which is in thee, and my wordes which I haue put into thee, ſhal neuer depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. And to the ende, they may growe vp and profit the better,<note place="margin">To make the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grow vp &amp; profit.</note> he ſealeth and marketh them with the ſeale and marke of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, adding moreouer an inwarde work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:7109:36"/>of his holy Ghoſte, and afterwarde gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them for meate and nouriſhment the Sacrament of the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſte, though he be able and ſufficient y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bring them to perfection in one houre. But it pleaſeth him to haue them growe vp after that forte by litle and litle, vnder the nouriſhement of this mother, ſo that who ſo is not conceyued in her wombe, and brought foorth by her, and foſtered and nouriſhed by her, doeth boaſt in vayne, that GOD is his Father:<note place="margin">Baſtarde children.</note> For he begetteth no children, neyther foſtereth and bringeth vp any, but by his miniſterie, ſo that we may not ſeperate theſe two thinges whiche God hath coupled togyther, to wit, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church is Mother to all them whoſe Father he is, and whoſoeuer is not begotten of her, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of an harlot and hathe an harlot for his mother, who begetteth children for the Deuill, &amp; to euerlaſting death: ſeeing there is no entrance into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life that remayneth for euer, but onely for them whom this mother kepeth, and guydeth, and gouerneth: ſo that who ſo is out of her boſome, it is impoſſible for him to be ſaued.</p>
               <p>And as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhly generation there is one lawful and an other baſtard, ſo fareth it alſo
<pb facs="tcp:7109:37"/>in the ſpirituall generation, there is one law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and an other baſtarde.<note place="margin">Two kindes of ſpirituall generation.</note> The firſt is after the ſpirit, and the ſecond after the fleſhe, and are hereby knowen the one from the other, that the one is conceyued and made by the ſpirit of trueth, of a chaſt mother, that is chaſt and faithful to her huſband IESUS Chriſt: and the other, by the ſpirit of errour and lyes, of a mother that playeth the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot with Satan, by breaking her promeſſe made to Chriſt, and yet notwithſtanding kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him with a trecherous kiſſe of Iudas: and lyke an hypocrite and diſſembling har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot as ſhe is, contenteth her ſelfe to haue but one halfe of him: the one being touched with a pure and naturall loue, will not haue him, vnleſſe ſhe may enioye him wholly, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore begetteth lawefull children, which are children of light, begotten of the immortall ſeede, and beautified with righteouſnes and holynes, to the ende ſayeth Saint Iames, that they may be the firſt fruites of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that is to ſay, choſen and ſet a part fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all other men, and ſequeſtred to be an holy offering: the other, on the contrarie ſide, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth children of darkenes to Satan, of a mortall ſeede, which are workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whoſe vnderſtanding is corrupt, going
<pb facs="tcp:7109:37"/>on from naught to worſe, as they are led by the ſpirit of lies, by whom the pure bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of true doctrine is ſtopped vp, and the ſeruice of God diſfigured with many kindes of ſuperſtitions, idolatrie and wickednes, &amp; yet vnder a coloure of godlynes, wiſedome, &amp; holines, wherby thei draw other into errour.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Amongſt al the baſtard children, the childe of perdition is the chiefeſt.</note>Amongeſt all the children thus begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the man of ſinne &amp; childe of Satan is moſt notorious, in whome the ſpirit of Satan dwelleth in all fulnes, as he doeth alſo in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which haue receiued his marke in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads and handes, and this man lifteth vp him ſelfe aboue all that is called God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue that thing whatſoeuer it be, wherin the worſhip of the Lord ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, which he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth to him ſelfe, in ſo much as he ſitteth in the temple of God, and maketh warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, with power of illuſion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueablenes, the like whereof was neuer ſeene, bearing a booke in his hand, which is ſweete in the hand, but bitter in the heart, &amp; ſo much the more deadly to the conſciences of men, by howe muche it is pleaſant to mans ſenſe and reaſone, and giueth him oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to boaſt of him ſelfe. To be ſhort this generation is a crooked, vnfaithfull, wicked, and froward generation, and yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:38"/>the number of them is great, they are farre mightier and of greater renowme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, which are but a ſmall flocke, vyle, abiect, and contemptible, as touching the fleſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fur prounteth the reache of our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>Now then, if the meanes of this genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Chriſtian man, wherby he is renued into a newe life, and made a newe creature, be founde to be ſuche that it ſurmounteth the capacitie of our ſenſes, we may not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile at it, ſeeing that euen in this bodily life, we perceiue ſuche a vertue, as the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherof our ſenſes are not able to atteine vnto. As for example, there is none of vs, but draweth the vital ſpirit of the ayre, and we al feele the motion of the ayre, wherby we both drawe in our breath, and breathe out, and yet there is not one of vs that can tel, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence this mouing commeth, or whither it goeth. And though euery one of vs feele in him ſelf the vertue of the ayre, yet we knowe not the beginning and the cauſe of it. Wel then, if in this tranſitorie life which is gone in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we ſee a marueilous vertue whereby God worketh ſo mightely in it, that it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the reache of our ſenſes, howe is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to fetch within the compaſſe of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding this ſecret worke in the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly
<pb facs="tcp:7109:38"/>life whiche paſſeth the reache of nature, as though we were not to beleue any more, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are able to perceiue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vewe of the eie:</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The light y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is giuen to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note>But the chiefeſt point that is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the excellencie of this generation is this, that euen as the word of God is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible ſeed of life, which bringeth forth fruite like to it ſelfe, and ſuche a budde as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer drieth vp: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo when the Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is once made partaker of this light, it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſo put forth and choked vp in him, but there remaineth ſtill ſome ſparke alway in him, ſuch is the force of the worde, when it is once kindled in the heart of man by the holy Ghoſt, who beareth him witnes that he is the childe of God, and cauſeth him to folowe his gouernement and conduct with a ſtedy heart, and holdeth him in a ſtedy and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall obedience of iuſtice. And therefore GOD ſayeth by his Prophet <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> That hee giueth them that are his, a newe heart, and promiſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they ſhal walke in his ordinances, for his holy ſpirit purſueth his grace in them, euen to the ende. For though there be ſometime ſome breaches &amp; cracks in their faith, as we haue alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in vs by reaſon of our frailenes, moued theru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to
<pb facs="tcp:7109:39"/>ſuch violence as Satan worketh againſt vs, and though the brightnes of our faith be daſeled with the thicke and obſcure darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of tentation: yet notwithſtanding it cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to haue alwayes an eye to God: and that more is, though it ſo fal out (as we know it befell to Dauid) that the Chriſtian man be for a ſeaſon ſo dead on ſleepe with ſuche a blockiſhnes of ſume, that there appeareth not any one ſparke of the ſpirit in him (as Dauid prayeth for this cauſe that it may be reſtored to him) yet notwithſtanding this ſeede, whereby God regenerateth his elect, as it is incorruptible dieth not, though it be for a ſeaſon as it were choked, ſo that a man would thinke, that all reuerence and feare of God were cleane put out. Yet there is a cole vnder theſe aſſhes, whiche kindleth and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth fyre againe, and this roote commeth to ſpurt forth, when a man would haue thought it had bene cleane dead. For the vertue and goodnes of God is ſuch, that it ſurmounteth our malice, ſo that, that man may be ſure of his ſaluation, whom God hath once touched with a liuely faith, though it were but a very ſhort whyle: for he is conſtrained to ſay, that that which he belieued, is a trueth, ſeeing it can not be by fleſhe &amp; blood, but by the light
<pb facs="tcp:7109:39"/>of God, wherein there is neither lie, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit: and ſo conſequently, that that hath bene once founde true, ſhalbe euer true.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The worke of the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of a Chriſtian is neuer left vs perfect.</note>For this is certaine that God, who began this worke of regeneration, will perfit it in the day of the Lorde, and will not leaue the worke of his handes vnperfect, for his gifts and callings are without repentance, &amp; looke what he hath once giuen, he neuer calleth it back, being faithfull &amp; conſtant in his deedes, and keepeth his trueth euerlaſtingly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any alteration or change, for it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible his worde ſhould faile: and it can not be but Gods decree muſt remaine according to the election, ſo that whomeſoeuer he hath once knowen and appointed to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that man can neuer fall from his ſaluation. The ſtedfaſtnes of his counſell is ſhewed to the heyres of promeſſe that it ſhall endure for euer, by two thinges whiche can neuer be changed, to witte, his worde, and his othe, whereby he hath confirmed his promiſſes, &amp; it is impoſſible he ſhould lye in them. To this purpoſe, Ieſus Chriſt ſayeth, that al that the father hath giuen him, ſhall come to him, and he wil not caſt out one of them that ſhal come to him. For this is the will of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſayth hee, that I leeſe not one of them
<pb facs="tcp:7109:40"/>whom my father hath giuen me, but I will rayſe them vp all in the latter day. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, My ſheepe, ſayth he, heare my voyce, and followe me, I knowe them, and giue them euerlaſting life, and no man ſhall take them out of myne hande. So then, ſeeing he hath promiſed that that man which hath once taken liuely roote in him, ſhall neuer be plucked vp, all that are of the flocke of his ſheepefolde, are out of daunger to be euer caſt away, becauſe the purpoſe of God which he hath decreed vpon them is ſtedfaſt, and the ſentence of peace is ratified to them, and therefore hee taketh them apart and ſayeth vnto them in this wyſe: feare not, litle flock, ſeeing it is giuen to you to know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſterie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of heauen: for to whom ſoeuer the gift of beleuing is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the ſame man is alſo giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance according to the vertue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt which is euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, wherby the Chriſtian man is, renued &amp; his force remaineth for euer: for otherwiſe were it not continuing for euer, the grace of God, could not be alwayes ſure and ſtable.</p>
               <p>And on the other ſide, it were to great &amp; doltiſhe blockiſhnes &amp; diſtruſt, to doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Sonne of God in his prayers for the Elect, that their faithe might not fayle
<pb facs="tcp:7109:40"/>them, were heard or no, ſeeing he ſanctified him ſelf for them, ſo that their hope which is as it were a ſure anchre for the ſoule, exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it ſelfe beyonde our death: and though the infirmitie of the fleſhe be great, yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their faſt holde hangeth not vpon their owne vertue, but vpon the vertue &amp; ſtrength of God, ſeeing their ſaluation is kept vnder his ſecret garde, as vnder a ſeale, and authe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſignet, they are out of all danger, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as it were, &amp; inregiſtred by the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and euerlaſting God in the booke of life, ſo that all their ſynnes are not able to ſtoppe the courſe of Gods election, nor quenche or diminiſhe the leſt wyſe that may be, the loue of God, ſeeing that euen by our verie ſinnes hee taketh occaſion to ſhewe vs farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loue, hee hym ſelfe beyng vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and his decrees euerlaſting, ſo that it is not in mans power to change his decree, nor to make him goe awaye from that whiche he hath once determined. And in deede, it were no meete thing for his vnchangeable nature, neither might it be truely ſayde of hym, that hee lighteneth men to blynde them, or buyldeth to pull downe, or planteth to roote vp.</p>
               <p>Hereby now may euery man ſee that the
<pb facs="tcp:7109:41"/>ſpirit of God,<note place="margin">Of the true marke of a Chriſtian.</note> is the true marke of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, whereby he is knowen from all other, and is of greater accompt then all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: not that Spirit whereby all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ſuſteined and haue their mouing by a generall ſtrength and vertue which is common to all liuing creatures, neither that ſpirit, whereby we haue diuers and ſundrie giftes beſtowed ſeuerally vpon eche of vs, but the ſpirit of adoption and ſanctification, which the Lorde giueth to none, but to the Chriſtian man, when he receiueth him into the number of his children, and ſeparateth him from all other, and ſundreth him from the world, to bring him to the hope of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting inheritance. This Spirit, is for this cauſe called the Spirit of ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereby the image of God is imprinted in a Chriſtian, and ſerueth him for an earneſt pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his ſaluation: and in deede putteth him in poſſeſſion and a certaine enioying of his adoption, whiche is giuen him by a ſpeciall grace of God, to bring that to paſſe by a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret working, which he determined in his ſecret counſel to bring to paſſe in him, by his mightie hand, ſhewing him ſelfe to be a moſt gracious and louing father by his teſtimony: a greater then which, and more certaine, we
<pb facs="tcp:7109:41"/>can not deſire, becauſe the light and knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which he giueth, is accompanied with ſuch a perſuaſion and certaintie of ſpirit, and with ſo ſtedfaſt and aſſured truſt of heart in his goodnes, that it maketh our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſurmount all thinges, clenſeth &amp; lifteth vp our hearts to heauen, and cauſeth vs to feele a ſpirituall taſt of heauenly riches. And to be ſhort, cauſeth a new birth in him, and tranſformeth him: for this light which is in a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mans ſoule, differeth very much fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all other light of knowledge, and from that kinde of faith which procedeth from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion of man. For it is impoſſible for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wit, to giue man ſuch vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and faith as this is, which is wrought in him by the mightie working of the ſpirit of God: and is this in ſumme, that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel which hath no appearance of witte nor ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, is notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding a wiſdom ſo high that it ſurmounteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauens, &amp; is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie power of God to ſaluation to euery one y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleueth to bring him to the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: for in deede, what can there be more ſtrange, more fooliſh, more ſimple, or more offenſiue to reaſon, then to heare a man ſay, that God is made &amp; become a mortall man, that life was ſubiect to death, righteouſnes
<pb facs="tcp:7109:42"/>couered with a ſhew of ſinne, bleſſing ſubiect to curſe, that by this meanes, men might be ranſomed from death, &amp; made partakers of bleſſed immortalitie, to the end they might obtein life, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> iuſtice might raigne, ſinne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once aboliſhed: and laſt of al to the end y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> death it ſelf &amp; malediction might be ſwalow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp, and therfore, that we haue to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to glorie by ignominie, into felicitie by my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, and into life by death.</p>
               <p>And moreouer that this light is farre dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from all other light of knowledge &amp; faith which proceadeth from the perſuaſion of man, it is nedeleſſe to alleage any other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the example of that faith, which is in the moſt part of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beare the name of Chriſtians, &amp; yet haue nothing but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bare ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and beleue in Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe they haue bene ſo learned &amp; taught fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> father to ſonne, &amp; are ſo perſuaded, becauſe they ſee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> liue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, beleue ſo: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially whom they take to be the holieſt, the wiſeſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt religious, &amp; perſuade them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their heades can not erre: So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if they had chanced to haue bene borne in any other countrie or religion, they would as eaſely haue bene perſuaded to it as to that which now they holde and are perſuaded is true,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:42"/>ſeeing their knowledge is gotten by reaſon and diſcourſe of man, not giuen of God and from aboue, but cold, fleſhly, weake, and very changeable which hath no other end but a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar reſpect of his owne, and nothing leſſe then to be touched with the glorie of God. Neither doe they receiue Ieſus Chriſte for ſuch an one, as he is offred of God the father in the Goſpel by a liuely faith proper to the elect, but while they profeſſe his name, they ſpoile him of his glorie, vertue, and dignitie, to tranſferre it to creatures and mens inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in ſteade of the Creator.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can not be knowen by the light of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſenſe</note>And therefore it foloweth, that this man which we ſpeake of, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be diſcerned from other by any iudgement of mans ſenſe &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but by a ſpiritual iudgement by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſpiritual things with ſpirituall things: for the Chriſtian people are but a ſmal flock, contemptible, ſcattred here one &amp; there one in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thickeſt of a number that are falſely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the people of God and Chriſtians, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> order of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſet apart as a treaſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God reſerueth for himſelf, hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; withdrawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight &amp; knowledge of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as a few graines of corne vnder a great deale of chaf in a floore: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, greatnes, wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or other appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb facs="tcp:7109:43"/>that man eſtemeth (be it neuer ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious) which we haue to reſpect, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> willeth the <hi>Corinth.</hi> to conſider, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there are but a few called amongſt them, a few wiſe, a few noble, a fewe mightie, &amp; of authoritie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh: neither haue we to reſpect the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, or outward profeſſion, ne yet the outward ſigne of Baptiſme, as it is written, All they that are of Iſrael, are not Iſraelites, nor all they Abrahams children, which are borne of Abraham, although they haue all one ſelfe ſame marke of Circumciſion: but it is the marke of the Spirit of God, which we muſt haue regard vnto, ſeeing that all ſignes and appearances, becauſe they are onely without, are vnprofitable, without the holy working of the inward, wherein truely conſiſteth the witneſſe, whereby a Chriſtian man may know him ſelf.<note place="margin">The onely marke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of God, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs to knowe a Chriſtian.</note> And the firſt effect of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vertue of God, is that which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture calleth Adoption, which is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the world, as Ieſus Chriſt giueth vs to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſaying, That he prayeth not the father for the world, but for them, whom the father hath giuen him, as it is ſaid in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiſe of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> adoption is not of men, but of God, according to his good pleaſure and grace giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt, before the
<pb facs="tcp:7109:43"/>foundations of the world were layde. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, euen as it is ſaid that Chriſt dwelleth in vs by the ſpirit of God, euen ſo doth man know, and is knowen to be a Chriſtian, by the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the ſame ſpirit, as by that marke wherewith the heauenly father ſealeth and marketh the heart of his elect in aſſurance of their adoptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; wherby he knoweth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath quickened fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen by his moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret vertue, which no ſenſe of man is able to perceiue, being in it ſelf very high &amp; of great maieſtie, &amp; in outward appeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vile &amp; beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly, wherby euery Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ſuch a conformitie with Chriſt, that as the world did not know him, ſo neither is he knowen to the world, for as much as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world which hath receiued nothing but the ſpirit of the world, hath no vnderſtanding of thoſe things which ſauor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of God. For, ſaith <hi>S. Paul</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as no man knoweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things that are in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of man, euen ſo no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the things of God, but the ſpirit of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How a man may knowe that he is a Chriſtian.</note>So then, a man can not iudge, no not of him ſelf, whether he be a Chriſtian or no, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be by the light of this ſpirit of God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is giuen him, as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> witneſſeth ſpeaking in the perſone of euerie Chriſtian, ſaying af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſort: Hereby we know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:7109:44"/>in vs, euen by the holy Ghoſt whom he hath giuen vs. And this he ſayeth vpon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine knowledge, &amp; not by geſſing, according to that that <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſayeth, That the ſame ſpirit beareth recorde with our ſpirit, that we are the children of God, and that it is not by the ſpirit of the worlde, but by the ſpirit of God, that we knowe thoſe thinges which are giuen vs of God, to wit, our adoption, &amp; hope of euerlaſting life, and more, that we are able to ſay and to ſay truely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are none of Chriſtes which haue not this inward wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſpirit: and againe, that they beare about them a witnes &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation againſt themſelues, which doubt whether they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe Chriſt and be of his bodie or no, hauing no aſſurance by certaintie of faith, to be out of doubt and vpon ſure ground both for this preſent and for the time to come, and ſuche faith as Ieſus Chriſt aſſureth vs, that al that are his ſhall haue, ſaying in this wiſe to his Apoſtles, the ſpirit of trueth which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world can not receiue, becauſe it ſeeth him not, ne knoweth him, but you knowe him, for he dwelleth in you,<note place="margin">Faith is not without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of continuance.</note> and ſhalbe in you. And in deede ſeeing that continuance is a neceſſarie thing for ſaluation, what faith were it if it had not with it aſſurance and certaintie to
<pb facs="tcp:7109:44"/>continue: Nowe the trueth is ſo, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath the gift of faith to beleeue, hath alſo the gift of perſeuerance to continue, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that faith is not a perſuaſion for a daye and a thing that ſodenly vaniſheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but a ſtedfaſt and well rooted perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the heart to continue all the life long, as ſaint Paule boaſteth boldely in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his election, and perſuadeth other to doe the lyke, vpon a glorie whiche is not grounded vpon any thing that is in man, but in the goodnes of God, ſaying, That hee knoweth, whome he beleeueth, and that he is one of them, whome Chriſt came to ſaue, that hee wayteth for the Croune of glorie, and is ſure that nothing can ſeparate him from the loue of God in Ieſus Chriſte, as one that was choſen before the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the worlde was layed. Whiche thing fleſhly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not do, becauſe they know not what the ſpirit of God meaneth, being not regenerate, and for that cauſe hauing ſo baſe an heart, ſo vite, and abiect through ſinne, that they can not perſuade them ſelues that God loued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo well, as to ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of his only &amp; derely beloued ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne: &amp; that he was ſo liberall, as to giue them paradiſe, vnleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:7109:45"/>they deſerue it by their workes and merites, where as the regenerate haue within them ſuch a feeling of the loue of God in Chriſt, that they ſee them ſelues out of doubt moſt aſſuredly ſaued in him, and can not perſuade them ſelues that Chriſt, to whom the father hath giuen all power to iudge, can pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſentence againſt thoſe his brethren and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, for whom he died vpon the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian by the effects of Gods ſpirit in him.</note>This chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath a certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by the effects which the ſame ſpirit of God bringeth forth in him, that he hath this gift of faith, for as ſone as hee cauſeth him through his vertue and mightie working to feele a peace and vnſpeakeable reſt in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that appeaſeth, contenteth and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth it, he mainteineth him in a ſpiritual ioy, increaſeth the ſtudie of good workes in him, inflameth him in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of God, maketh him delight in his word, &amp; in the ſame word to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the face of God, gracious, louing, and fauourable, with ſuche an aſſurance of his grace, that he reioyceth and triumpheth with a bolde and cherefull countenance in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hope of euerlaſting glorie, in ſo muche that he is not afrayed to preſent him ſelfe before his God, and call vpon hym as his father, with perfect aſſurance to obteine at his handes
<pb facs="tcp:7109:45"/>what ſoeuer is neceſſarie for him: whiche were impoſſible for him to do, if he were not moued &amp; enforced thereunto through ſome heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly and diuine working which ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all the force and ſtrength that is or can be in man. For from whence might this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of the good wil of God procede, and that the man is colde and altogyther ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of him ſelfe, voyd of al motion or bent to pray to him, could be moued to repayre vnto him with ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence, and yet godly not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, hauing grieuouſly offended him, were it not through his diuine and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly working? whiche the Chriſtian man may eaſely perceyue moreouer by this, that it engendreth in him a loue of Iuſtice, and on the other ſide, a hatred of ſinne, by an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of affections, pleaſures and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for other then before, to wit, ſuche as are in al them, whoſe eyes the Prince of this worlde hath blinded. And yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding trueth it is that he feeleth a continuall combat of the ſpirit and the fleſh in him ſelf, whiche hindereth him from perfecting his workes, but yet ſo it is, that though ſin dwell in him, yet it doeth not reigne in him. And ſuch are the effectes, whereby the Chriſtian man commeth to the experience and feeling
<pb facs="tcp:7109:46"/>of his fayth, &amp; ſo conſequently of his electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>For a Chriſtian man ſtriueth not to enter into the Sanctuarie of Gods wiſedome to informe him ſelfe of Gods predeſtination, &amp; ſecret counſell, as ſome raſhe headed &amp; more bold then godly wyſe will nedes intrude and thruſt in them ſelues moſt arrogantly in to the ſecretes of God, finding nothing in the ende, but a maſe which they are neuer able to get out of: for neyther is it meere that the height of the wiſedome of God ſhoulde be ſubiect to the ſenſe of man, to ſeeke it out euen to his euerlaſtingnes. But the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian being once come to the way of fayth, &amp; holding him ſelfe ſtedfaſtly there, is led from ſtep to ſtep euen to the King of heauens cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi> ſpeaketh, there to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the treaſure of his Election, and yet for all that doeth not become thereby negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and diſſolute, but cleane contrarie, doth after that more diligently applie him ſelfe to God,<note place="margin">Man is not made negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent by kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wing that he is choſen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o lyfe.</note> to be his inſtrument of righteouſnes, continuing moſt reuerently to make his ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction more ſteady and ſure by good workes, which God hath prepared for his Elect to walke in.</p>
               <p>But we muſt vnderſtande that this light whiche is in the children of God, whereby
<pb facs="tcp:7109:46"/>they haue this knowledge in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues that they are Chriſtians,<note place="margin">To know in an other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide him ſelf, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be a Chriſtian or no.</note> reacheth to no further aſſurance then of them ſelues: for they are not able to knowe aſſuredly of an other man that that they knowe to be in them ſelues, by reaſon of that hypocriſie that is naturally in the heart of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wholly diſguyſed and ſeaſed with a thouſand kinde of maſkings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he deceyueth not onely other men, but him ſelfe alſo: and moreouer becauſe this priuiledge of ſounding mens hearts, &amp; kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing men within, belongeth properly to God alone, who hath reſerued to him ſelfe the knowledge of his, as he keepeth them cloſe vnder his ſeale, as S. Paul ſayeth, yea at ſuch time as when they do not as yet ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowe him, or them ſelues. Surely the ſight of man is too weake to enter ſo farre as to iudge aſſuredly whether the ſeede of the word of God be rooted deepe ynough in any mans heart to remayne there. And to the end he ſhould not raſhly take ſo much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, God hath taken a good order for it, warning vs dayly by experience, howe farre his ſecret iudgements paſſe our capacitie: for oftentimes we ſee thoſe men brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the right way, whiche ſeemes to vs to be vtterly caſt away and loſt children. As on the
<pb facs="tcp:7109:47"/>other ſide, we ſee a nomber fal, which ſeemed to vs to ſtand very faſt, being true as <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> ſayeth, That according to the ſecret and hidden counſell of God, there are many ſheepe without the Church, &amp; many wolues within. And in deede there is in a nomber ſuch a likelyhood and reſemblance of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, vnder a cloake of hypocriſie, that they ſeeme to haue the ſelfe ſame beginning and grounde of fayth, which the Chriſtian hath, which cauſeth vs that we can not iudge of them aright as we ſhould. For moreouer &amp; beſide that they haue the ſelf ſame name that the other haue,<note place="margin">The hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie of the falſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hath great affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with the true.</note> and be likewiſe in the ſelfe ſame companie, make profeſſion of one ſelfe ſame doctrine, receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Sacraments, they are ſometimes touched with ſome taſte of the worde of God, and do reuerence it, yea and that ſo far forth that they thinke it great impietie to contemne it and deſpiſe it: and haue moreouer ſuch a taſte of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly gifts, as the Apoſtle him ſelfe witneſſeth in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hebrewes, that thei ſeeme both to them ſelues and to other that ſee them, to be no leſſe acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted of then the reſt of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And yet it falleth out ſo in the end, that they ſhewe them ſelues to be nothing leſſe then Chriſtians, thus deceyuing them ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:7109:47"/>within them ſelues, becauſe they can not throughly examine them ſelues in their heartes, nor make good profe of them ſelues whether Chriſt dwel in them or no, ſo full of vanitie is the heart of man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the true and counterfei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſtian.</note>For thus it is, that the ſeede of the worde of God hath not life in them to continue and dwell there without corruption: though it ſeeme to haue taken roote in them, yet it is not liuely, ſo that, the taſte which they get of the goodnes of God, is but for a whyle, and yet that too very confuſed, and very irreſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute: and in like ſort, in that that God lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth their vnderſtandings and maketh them knowe his grace, it is without ingrauing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> true efficacie in them, which is imprinted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtians heart, which they neuer knew, becauſe they receyue not the vertue of the Spirit of GOD in deede, ne haue the true clearenes of fayth but onely to ſerue them for greater condemnation, and make them voyde of all excuſe. And in that that God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into their heartes, it is to no other ende but that his bountie and trueth may be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to them by the Spirit of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, without further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating with them, the Spirit of adoption. And this is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, why through want of ablenes to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende
<pb facs="tcp:7109:48"/>his vnchangeable will, they can not conſtantly embrace his trueth to haue more then a light and ſly knowledge of it, nor haue an earneſt deſire to loue God heartily as his children do. Hereof it followeth, that a man can no more know certaynely,<note place="margin">It is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to know who is a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian before he dye.</note> whether an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man be a true Chriſtian or no, then he can in a ground ſowed with diuers ſeedes, knowe one ſeede from another, which ſhall bring forth fruit &amp; which ſhal not, yea though it haue already put forth, yea and that more is, though it be al eared. Wherefore euen as <hi>Solon</hi> ſayed to <hi>Creſus</hi> King of <hi>Lydia,</hi> that no man is to be counted happie before his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes day, becauſe of many miſeries and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities which may befall him: euen ſo I ſay, that no one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can know an other man tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly to be a Chriſtian, (whiche is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt felicitie that is) before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of his race. And for this ende and purpoſe <hi>Ieſus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> warneth vs to iudge of no man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death, becauſe, ſayeth he, that is the time wherein a man ſheweth what he hath bin all his lyfe long. For ſome ſhew euident tokens, that they were neuer other before God but Chriſtians, though whyle they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, they neuer made any ſhewe of it: other ſome, that thei were neuer Chriſtians, thogh
<pb facs="tcp:7109:48"/>they made ſhewe of that profeſſion a great nomber of yeeres: for witnes wherof, let vs take Iudas on the one ſide, and the thief that was hanged with Chriſt on the other. This is a poynt which we muſt alwayes haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vnto, that ſuch as God hath choſen to be true Chriſtians, ſhalbe true Chriſtians, what malice &amp; vnbeliefe ſoeuer they be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently giuen vnto: and they alſo on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, of whome he hath foreſeene that they ſhall be wicked and infidels, ſhalbe ſuch be they neuer ſo good and of a true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion at this inſtant: for he is a Chriſtian alwayes, which hath bin foreknowen and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted before from the beginning to be a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A Chriſtian man may be knowen by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie, and how?</note>So then it appeareth that there is great difference betwene that iudgement whiche a Chriſtian man may make of him ſelfe, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> iudgement which he can make of an other man, becauſe the certeintie of faith remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſhut vp within, and ſtretcheth not ſo far as to be knowen in other, ſeeing that the Spirit of GOD beareth all the elect wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their calling. But as for an other man, wee knowe not howe to iudge of him, ſaue onely by the outwarde man, whiche is often tymes very deceyueable.
<pb facs="tcp:7109:49"/>And yet notwithſtanding by the iudgement of charitie we may accompt him for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, in whom we finde, (ſo farre as the eye of man is able to reach) the ſeede of the word not to be fruitleſſe, that is to ſay, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpel is not only in worde, but in vertue of the holy Ghoſt, conſidering that where we ſee the ſignes of Gods election as we take them, there we haue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hope well, and not defraude our neighbour of a charitable, friendly, and louing iudgement. For moreouer and beſide that the good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which ought to be in a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leadeth vs to hope well of all men. S. Paul writing to the Theſſalonians, is ſo bolde as to aſſure them, that their election is of God, ſpeaking as it were vpon a certaintie of knowledge grounded vpon notable ſignes and markes of the vertue of the holy Ghoſt, which he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he ſawe in them, by euident effectes of fayth, the carefull and paynefull charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their neighbours, the ſure hope and ſtedfaſt continuance in wayting for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of Ieſus Chriſte, with pacience which ſurmounteth all wearines both of the length of time, and of all afflictions of the world whatſoeuer. The like he doeth parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in Timothies reſpect, to whome he
<pb facs="tcp:7109:49"/>writeth, That he aſſureth him ſelf that faith and true religion dwelleth in him, iudging ſo of the certeintie of the cauſe which is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to all men, by the apparant effects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, euen as if it were viſible. And ſo we in like ſorte, by a charitable iudgement, may iudge, or at the leaſt, perſwade our ſelues wel of our brethren, in whom we perceyue like fruites and actions of the Spirit of God, to take &amp; accompt them for Chriſtians. For as we iudge by the outward motions of the bodie, that there is a ſoule in the bodie: ſo may we perceyue by his workes whether the ſpirit of God be in man or no, ſeeing that euen as the ſoule which liueth not idle within mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ſheweth it ſelf by that vertue and vigour which it diſtributeth to the members, and to eche part of the bodie: euen ſo the Spirit of God that is in man, is not idle but ſheweth what power it is of, in the man in whome it is: and ſheweth it ſelfe effectually by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie with Chriſt who liueth in him, and gyueth life to his members whiche he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth with them, and powreth out vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them by the vertue of his Spirit, which is, as you would ſay, the general ſoule of al the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, not reſpecting the ſubſtance, but the grace: ſo that, euen as we thinke that
<pb facs="tcp:7109:50"/>the graffe is well ioyned to the ſubſtance of the tree which it is graffed into, when we ſee it bring forth fruite out of the ſame tree, by that ſtrength which it receyueth of the ſame roote: euen ſo we know that a man is truely ingraffed and made one body with Chriſt, when through one ſelfe ſame force of the Spirit, he bringeth forth fruit in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To know a reprobate man.</note>But as for the knowledge of a reprobate man, it is a thing ſo ſecret and hidde to men, that they can neuer iudge of it certeinly, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they haue ſome extraordinarie reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for be it that we finde neuer ſo euil ſignes and tokens in any man, what is he that can tell whether God haue reſerued mercy for him in ſtore or no, vnto the latter ende of his lyfe, though he haue ſpent it wholly in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe? Therefore ſeeing in deede it was not expedient nor mete for vs to haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to diſcerne the one from the other, leſt that thereby we ſhoulde become to colde in charitie towardes all, as we owe to all, as though all men were our brethren in Chriſt, it is ſufficient that this chaffe ſhall be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the corne at the latter day. So then this onely remayneth, that we knowe diſtinctly and particularly, what the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt in man are, becauſe there
<pb facs="tcp:7109:50"/>is no other way to knowe a Chriſtian man outwardly by, but by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To knowe a Chriſtian man by the outward ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes of the holy Ghoſt in him.</note>And ſeeing it is ſo as we haue ſaide, that a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, is a man made a new creature as touching his nature, by a ſeconde byrth, it is euident, that that can not be done vnleſſe the firſt nature dye, and this man put of the fleſhe, that is to ſay, his firſt nature which is corrupt, euen that which we bring with vs from our mothers wombes, which is called the old man. For he can not in any wyſe be capable of the kingdome of heauen, vnleſſe he be deſtroyed and brought to naught by the ſworde of the Spirit, to the ende that death may make a riddance of all the operacions of the fleſhe, which ſinne woorketh in him. For as long as we are Adams children, and nothing els but men, we are ſuche ſlaues to ſinne, that we can do nothing but ſinne, vntil we be made new men by the death of the firſt man, and haue paſſed by meanes of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of the death of Chriſt to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of his life. Theſe two pointes, to wit, Mortification, and Viuification,<note place="margin">Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, two of the chiefeſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Spirit of God in a Chriſtian.</note> whiche can not be ſeparate the one from the other, are out of doubt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefeſt operations of the holy Ghoſt in a Chriſtian man: ſo that, euen as Chriſte dyed to deſtroy ſinne, paſſing by
<pb facs="tcp:7109:51"/>death to euerlaſting lyfe, in that fleſhe which he toke of vs: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo this man is dead in him ſelfe, and renued to a better life, accompanied with meete &amp; conuenient workes for it: and ſuch as may witnes that he is a trewe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt, by caſting downe of him ſelfe, of his owne wiſedome, and reaſon, and al his affections and paſſions, which caſting downe of him ſelfe proceedeth from a liuely taſt and feeling of the goodnes of our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereby man is knowen to be Gods chylde, and inheritour of al his bleſſings: for this can not be, but forthwith his vyle, baſe, carnal and earthely affections vaniſhe away and become dead in him, by reaſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great light of fayth, which darkeneth &amp; putteth out all the falſe light of our corrupt nature.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, a Chriſtian man doeth then in deede ſhewe him ſelfe to be a right Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when the death of Chriſt, which hath a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne force in it to expell and caſt out the wickednes of our fleſhe, and his reſurrection whereby there is rayſed vp in vs the ſtate &amp; condition of a better nature, ſhew their fruit in him, as by Baptiſme we are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of this grace. So that al knowledge of Ieſus Chriſte, that hath not this vertue to followe it, is naked and bare, and al baptiſme
<pb facs="tcp:7109:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>without it vnprofitable and nothing worth: for there commeth no man to Chriſt, or is receyued into the grace of Chriſt, but the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie of his death appeareth in him, &amp; bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth about a ſhew and token of it in him by mortification of the fleſh, and quickening of the ſpirit, as hauing paſſed out of this firſt nature, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of Chriſt by a ſpirituall renewing, which ſheweth it ſelfe by framing the courſe of our life anew, wherein who ſo is formoſt, ſheweth that he hath profited moſt in the knowledge of God: And we may not thinke that the benefit of the death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt belongeth to any other, ſaue onely to them which ſhew forth a new lyfe, &amp; of a right affection of heart, ſome ſooner, ſome later, giue them ſelues to holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and cleannes, wherein ſtandeth the band of the coniunction that is betwene God and vs, and the certayne badge and marke of a Chriſtian man, wherby the children of God, as S. John ſayth, are knowen from the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the deuill.</p>
               <p>For which cauſe, Ieſus Chriſt ſpeaking of this ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Holynes of lyfe is a marke of a Chriſtian.</note> as of a true marke wherby his are knowen, ſayed, that it is the wedding garment, whereby as by the bridegromes cloth &amp; liuerie, thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:7109:52"/>to the mariage feaſt are knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And the Apoſtle ſayth to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that without this cleannes no man can ſee God, nor be ioyned to him, to cleaue faſt to him. And it is impoſſible for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be in one, but the ſpirit of ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt alſo nedes be in him: for by it, it is that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful are called Saincts, as ſanctified &amp; made holy of God, conſecrated &amp; ſet apart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prophane &amp; common vſe, &amp; ſeparated from al earthly filthines &amp; defyling of the fleſh, as the veſſels, garments, temples, &amp; ſwete ſinelling ſacrifices were, which might not be applyed to any other vſe, but that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was holy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate to the glorie of God. For it is meete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they that are lightened with the doctrine of ſaluation, ſhould ſhewe them ſelues an other ſort of men, then they that walke after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of their owne braines, being ouercoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with darknes, becauſe they neuer felt any light of trueth: ſo that to finde an holy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in deede (which is the Chriſtian man) we neede not ſeeke him in an heremitage or deſert,<note place="margin">An holy man.</note> or in ſome cloſe place that is walled about, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the conuerſation and common life of men, eyther in garments, meate, ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, or what other obſeruation ſoeuer of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible things, and other forme of holynes
<pb facs="tcp:7109:52"/>inuented by men, with a kinde of wiſedome in ſuperſtition and humblenes of ſpirit, and contempt of the body vnder a cloke of fayned obedience, pleaſant in ſhew to mans reaſon: but in the onely working of the holy Ghoſt, which tranſformeth ſoules into that holynes which he hath him ſelf, and frameth them in ſuch wyſe to newe thoughts and affections, that we may welſay, they are other then they were before, as wrought in his knowledge and to his image that made them.</p>
               <p>Which thing appeareth not only within through an inward and ſpirituall feeling of a pure conſcience cleanſed from wicked affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, aſſiſted thereunto with a feare of God, and faith, and hope, and patience, and inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but alſo without through a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of godlynes, voyde of all ſuperſtition, which might leſſen or darken the glorie of God, by giuing that to other which is propre to him: as alſo by peace and ioy of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, meekenes, goodnes, vpright dealing, iuſtice, ſobrenes, temperancie, &amp; other fruites of the Spirit, contrarie to the fruites of the fleſhe, whiche are, vncleannes, filthines, idolatrie, ſectes, hereſies, diſſolutenes, enimities, ſediti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, outrages, murders, theftes, &amp; other ſuch like, which are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to brotherly charitie,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:53"/>which Ieſus Chriſt telleth vs, is an other marke &amp; toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Charitie a marke of Chriſtians.</note> wherby they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are his are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be his diſciples: not only by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon loue towards al men, as al men are one fleſhe, and al created and faſhioned to the image of God, but alſo by a ſpecial &amp; mutuall loue the one towards the other, ſo much the more ſtraight and preciſe, by how much the image of God ſhineth more clearely in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom he hath before regenerate.</p>
               <p>And therfore, as by mortifying of him ſelf, the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man forgetteth himſelf, &amp; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is about him, to liue in God, referring the partes of his life to him, as to their onely end, without further ſearche of things that pleaſe him ſelfe, but ſuche onely as pleaſe him, and as he well lyketh of for the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement of his glorie: and ſo by this way &amp; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of mortification, he caſteth of al conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of him ſelf, and layeth aſide all fleſhly affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to giue him ſelf wholly to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and preferreth the profit of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,<note place="margin">A differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene Charitie and the loue of our ſelues.</note> before any reſpect of him ſelf: So that this loue is an other manner of loue, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that naturall loue which is common to all men, which is nothing els, to ſpeake truely, but a loue of our ſelues, accordingly as euery man is inclined to haue a care of him ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:53"/>and ſo to ſeeke his owne profyte and gayne: neither is there any more agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, then is betweene fyre and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for the loue of our ſelues keepeth all our ſenſes ſo well occupied, that this Chriſtian and brotherly loue, is wholly baniſhed. And therefore <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſayeth playnely, That all they that haue a right feeling of it, knowe that they are paſſed from death to life, and they that haue no feeling of it, remaine in death, that is to ſay, thei y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are not regenerat.</p>
               <p>And in deede, the bond of perfection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in loue, for loue is the marke and end whereat the Lawe ſhooteth, and wherin the end of ſanctification ſtandeth, as whereby e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of vs hath to witnes to the world, what loue we beare to God, whom we loue in our brethren. Conſidering that this loue is ſo ioyned and coupled with the loue of God, that it can in no wyſe be ſeparate from it, becauſe it procedeth from the loue of God. as the effect from the cauſe: and in this it is, to be ſhort, wherein ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the right rule of life, whereby the Chriſtian man frameth all his actions and moderateth the right vſe of the giftes of God. And therefore whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is not ſquared by it, is falſe, and all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues be they neuer ſo excellent, are without
<pb facs="tcp:7109:54"/>it, nothing els but a wynde that puffeth men vp with pryde and vanitie, and a vaine pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or vnprofitable ſound, that is to ſaye, a thing of nothing, and that more is, a ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and abominable thing before God.</p>
               <p>And therefore we muſt not thus thinke of a Chriſtian man, that he is a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen a ſide from all other men, liuing in a ſolitarie place,<note place="margin">A Chriſtian man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draweth not him ſelf fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doing.</note> or ſo dedicate to a contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>platine life, as they call it, as that thereby he is diſtract from ſuch actions of conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as are behoueable and neceſſarie for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terteinement of the ſocietie of men. Seing that men are borne one for an other, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate one with an other for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the ſocietie of mankinde, and not to bereue our neighbours of that duetie we owe them, if we wil not be taken for theeues before God. Conſidering that we were not placed here in this world, to liue ſolitarily as wylde and brute beaſtes, but to liue amongſt companie, and to make other men partakers of that which God hath beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eche of vs, and there is nothing wherein men are ſaid to followe God ſo muche in, as in em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying them ſelues charitably one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the profit of one an other, as in deede that vertue is the beſt of all, that is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:7109:54"/>to the moſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ployeth him ſelfe to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry trade of life, both pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uate and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique.</note>Therefore the Chriſtian, is a man that hath dayly conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with other men, that applieth him ſelfe indifferently to all condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and trades of life, whereunto he findeth him ſelfe rightly called, and therein employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him ſelfe faithfully to the profit of the ſocietie of mankinde, whether it be in reſpect of a priuate life and the dealinges thereunto belonging, or in regarde of the common weale, whiche is to be folowed without his owne houſe: So that as a ſonne he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the duetie of obedience and ſubiection to his father and mother, and helpeth them as much as he can: as a ſeruant, he ſheweth him ſelfe ſeruiceable to his maſter,<note place="margin">The priuate ſtate.</note> and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to pleaſe him, as of a free and wylling heart, ſeruing God and not man: as on the other ſyde, if he be a maſter, hee entreateth his ſeruantes gentlye, and is not to rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and churliſhe towardes them, hauing alwayes an eye to God, as to the Lorde and Maſter of all: and if he be a Father, he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his children louingly and gentlye as is meete for their perſones, trayneth vp and frameth theyr lyues in good maners: and laſt, if hee be an husbande, he rendreth that beneuolence, that is due vnto his wife,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:55"/>for we may not thinke, that this man is of the number of thoſe, whiche forſake the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy that God hath eſtabliſhed for auoiding of fornication, and will nedes vpon an headi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ouercome the neceſſitie of nature, raſhly aſſuring them ſelues that God will helpe them, which he promiſeth to none but to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that walke in his wayes, ne giueth the gift of continencie at all times to all men. Moreouer the order and frame of an houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, is ſo well perceiued in the houſe of a Chriſtian, that he him ſelf as Paſtoure of his familie, inſtructeth it diligently in the feare of God, and keepeth it in good and Godly diſcipline by continual exerciſe in Godlines. So that in his houſe, you ſhall finde the chaſt wife, the ſhamefaced, plaine, &amp; modeſt wife, decked without as ſhe is within, no painted nor masked thing, rendring true obedience to her husband, and hauing an eye vpon her familie, her ſeruants, her children: the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, father, and husbande, euery one in his degree employing him ſelfe ſyncerely in his duetie and office, approuing his doings as before God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſtate.</note>And as for other offices &amp; dealings which are not houſhold matters, and are without his houſe, as an inferiour and ſubiect, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenceth
<pb facs="tcp:7109:55"/>the higher powers, &amp; ſubmitteth him ſelfe willingly to them, as to Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, whoſe minde is by this order, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the worlde and keepe the ſtate of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde in peace and tranquillitie, payeth them their tributes and dueties, and ſubmitteth him ſelfe freely and frankely to obey their lawes and commandementes, not onely for neceſſities ſake, becauſe he can not reſiſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without danger of being puniſhed for it, but alſo for conſcience ſake, bound to do it by the worde of God. He honoreth the Miniſters &amp; Paſtours of the Church, as Gods meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and ſheweth him ſelf ready and frame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their teaching, frequenteth the holy aſſemblies, and vſeth all meanes he can, that are profitable to nouriſhe and mainteine the ſeruice of God. And againe, as ſuperiour and placed in higher roume aboue other, he hath a care to execute his charge faithfully, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the good, puniſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked, as al power and authoritie of man, is bound to ſerue the commoditie and profit of the ſubiects. If he be a paſtour, he miniſtreth the world of God faithfully, and marreth not the doctrine of ſaluation, he keepeth it in his puritie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth the people both in good doctrine &amp; in good example of life, and vſurpeth no rule
<pb facs="tcp:7109:56"/>or violent &amp; tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous Lordlines ouer his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes nor inferiours, but ſeketh the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie and profite of all them that hee hath charge of.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Where there is mutuall charitie, there is alſo mutuall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude.</note>So then the condition of all men is this, that they are mutually bounde one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo that none of vs may exempt him ſelfe from ſubiection, and therefore whereſoeuer there is loue of one toward an other, there is alſo interchangeable ſeruice. The higheſt Kings and Princes that are, are not exempt from it, for God hath placed them in pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence to ſerue, as the members of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, what preeminence and prerogatiue ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the one hath ouer the other, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſerue one an other, vſing ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as God hath put in them, to the profit of the whole bodie, receiuing no other commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie but that which ariſeth of the profite of the whole, and is powred out vpon the whole bodie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian loketh alwayes to his calling.</note>And for this cauſe, the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man hath his eyes alwayes bent vpon his vocation, as vpon aprinciple and ground whereby to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne him ſelf a right, neceſſarie in al things to keepe the right waye, taketh heede he do not ambitiouſly and raſhlye, take vpon him many and ſondrie charges and offices togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:56"/>that he attempt not more then his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling will beare, and medleth not raſhly with thoſe things which do nothing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne him, but contenteth him ſelfe with his preſent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, whatſoeuer it be, whether great or ſmal, rich or poore, honorable or baſe, he fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth it and continueth in it conſtantly, and paſſeth not his bounds, nor changeth it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſt cauſe. For his affections are ruled, &amp; he bridleth his naturall &amp; inordinate deſires which couet commonly more then ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath, meaſuring his ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie by the will of God, which he knoweth by that that befalleth him: and taketh all as from him, and by his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whereunto he referreth the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of him ſelfe, and whatſoeuer concerneth him, ſo that he wil do nothing, nor take ought vpon him of his owne head, but as a ſimple toole &amp; inſtrument ſubmitteth himſelf to the conduct of his maſter and workeman, who is the Lord of all.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with his ſtate.</note>And therfore in what ſtate ſoeuer he finde him ſelf, either high or lowe, rich or poore, he beareth him ſelfe alwayes moderatly and as it were, in an euen balance. Hauing aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of richeſſe, honours, and heauenly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges, plentifully poured vpon his ſoule, hee eaſely frameth hym ſelfe to beare hym
<pb facs="tcp:7109:57"/>ſelfe after one forte in what ſo euer ſtate may befall him in this preſent life, making nothyng ſo great accompt of earthly and tranſitorie things,<note place="margin">The quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a Chriſtian.</note> as men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly do verie vainely and fooliſhly. To be ſhort, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, is a veſſel of honour, ſanctified to euerie good worke, and a man that walketh after the ſpirit, and not after the fleſh, and as Ieſus Chriſt ſayth, that bringeth forth good things out of the treaſure of his heart and ſpirituall vertue that is in him: for he is the good tree which is knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his good fruite it beareth. And a man clad with the garment of light, that walketh honeſtly as at midday in all mens eyes, being a paterne of good workes, and a lampe lightened with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, that ſhineth in the darkenes of the world by purenes of life, in whom there is not one piece or portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his life, but yeldeth a good and ſweete ſauour of holines &amp; loue to the glorie of God, and profit of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, whether we marke his talke, which is poudred with ſalt, accordingly as the worde of God dwelleth plentifully in him, and with ſuch a grace, that he is able to draw his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers by reaſon of the commoditie and profit that commeth by his talke, either to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt behauiour, being very meeke and graue,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:57"/>or to his actions which tende to nothing but to goodnes &amp; honeſtie before men, labouring by his good conuerſation to edifie all men to the aduancement of their ſaluation. And all this he doeth, becauſe he feeleth within hym ſelfe that he is called to ſo high a degree of honour as to be the childe of God, which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him with great earneſtnes, and zeale of ſpirite to do an infinite ſort of good workes to the glorie of God, and to frame himſelfe to be manered and facioned as becommeth ſo high a ſtate as he is placed in.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marke of the croſſe</note>And though theſe markes may ſeeme to be ſufficient to knowe a true Chriſtian by, yet notwithſtanding beſide thoſe markes of holines and charitie, there is the marke of the croſſe, farre more apparant and to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in the ſight of man, to teache vs more plainely that the knowing of a Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtandeth in the mortification of the outward man outwardly, as the former did in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man. And yet both the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceede out of one head, which is the felowſhip we haue with Chriſte, which can not be ſeparate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe. For this cauſe the doctrine of the Goſpel is called the word of the Croſſe, becauſe the worlde doeth for the moſt parte, hate it, as the wiſdome of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7109:58"/>is wholly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to the wiſedome of God: the one ſeeking Gods glorie, the other, the glorie of the fleſh, which is ſo much the more enemy to the firſt, becauſe the light of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel diſcouereth the darknes of it, &amp; the trueth of the Goſpel maketh manifeſt and bringeth to light the errours and lies of the fleſh. And becauſe the world can not indure it, &amp; ſeeth that it can not mainteine it ſelf in credit, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> may of trueth and peace, it ſtriueth to do it by the way of lying, cogging, and violence, as it is in deede a lier &amp; murderer: ſo that they that are accompted and taken for the wiſeſt, the diſcreteſt, of greateſt power and holines, are ſometimes the firſt that band them ſelues againſt the trueth of God, as they that feele them ſelues moſt greeued. And therfore the Iewes did more hainouſly a great deale per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute Chriſt then the Gentiles, &amp; amongſt them the Phariſies and high Prieſts more then the common people: and ſo at this day, the chiefeſt among the falſe Chriſtians and members of Antichriſte, are enemies to Chriſt, more than other, ſo that the ſaying of ſaint Paule is found true in all times, That they which are after the fleſh, alwayes perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that are after the ſpirit, for though they do not impriſon all, nor baniſh all, nor
<pb facs="tcp:7109:58"/>confiſcate all Chriſtians goodes, nor burne all, or behead all, or hang all, yet at the leſt wyſe, there are fewe that ſcape their ſcoffes and mockes, their reuiles and tantes, their gnaſhing of teeth and ſhaking their heads at them. for this is a ſure ſaying and worthy to be receyued, that all that will liue fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye in Jeſus Chriſte, muſt ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Chriſtian is to beare the croſſe.</note>So that all the children of God haue this condition layed vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to beare the croſſe of Chriſt, as men appointed to it, by the wyll of the heauenly Father, who hath decreed this with him ſelfe to obſerue this order and meanes in gouerning his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he wil exerciſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this life with diuers croſſes: and for that cauſe Jeſus Chriſt him ſelfe the elder brother was conſecrate by afflictions, and ſo entred into the preferrement of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And ſo muſt all they that followe him, beare the ſame liuerie and cogniſſance vpon them, as he him ſelfe ſhewed plaine inough, ſaying to his Apoſtles, No man can be ſaid to be his diſciple, but he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> taketh vp his croſſe &amp; foloweth him. And in an other place, That the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God ſhalbe knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other by this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world ſhal hate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as he was hated firſt. And in deede if we looke vpon Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7109:59"/>the paterne of our faith, which is a ſufficient example for vs,<note place="margin">Abraham a paterne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtians.</note> ſo that we neede not alleage any other, we may ſee that the promiſſe of adoption was no ſoner made him, but he was by and by commaunded to depart from his houſe, and forſake his parentes, his own cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, to be a pilgryme and a ſtranger vpon the earth, ſubiect to a perpetuall kinde of croſſe. And ſurely that man can not haue a certain profe within him ſelf, that he is a Chriſtian, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is vnwilling to be ſubiect to this ſtate &amp; condition, which the maſter, &amp; head, and Lord of al, was willingly ſubiect to, for vs all, &amp; who is a liuely paterne for vs to folowe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to Chriſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Croſſe.</note>For the free adoption, wherein conſiſteth mens ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, can not be ſeparate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods euerlaſting decree, which hath made all his children ſubiect to beare the Croſſe: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there ſhalbe none inheritour of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is not firſt made like to the only ſonne of God. For as he hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefeſt &amp; beſt place amongeſt al the children of God, as amongſt men, the eldeſt ſonne beareth the name of the houſe: ſo is he appointed to be their paterne, by whom they muſt be framed as it were by line and ſquare, to the end they refuſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which he was ſubiect vnto: and that
<pb facs="tcp:7109:59"/>in ſo doing, they may euerie one in his place, be ioyned and coupled together with their head, who is placed in the higheſt degree, not onely to be aboue all, but alſo to holde all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are coupled togither with him vnder one ſelfſame marke of brotherhood and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. And as kings &amp; princes of this world, haue their honours and praiſes, wherewith they crowne the noble and valiant actes of their ſoldiers: ſo this ſoueraigne King and Prince Jeſus Chriſt honoreth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with his markes, whom he vſeth in matters of great weight, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende they may appeare glorious with him aboue the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A difference betwene the croſſe of the Chriſtians, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly croſſes.</note>Hereby it appeareth, how farre this marke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe which is proper to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world taſteth of, ſeing the caſe ſtandeth ſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can ſay, that he is exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſerie, affliction, &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in this life. For where as the other which al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taſte of, is a ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſe of God to the wicked, this croſſe which is ſanctified of God, is a ſigne of bleſſing, &amp; wholſom for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beare it, &amp; therefore they ſhould be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhould thinke, that they which ſuffer in this warfare againſt ſinne, ſhould be thought to ſuffer for ſinne, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worldlings do in their ſuffera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by this croſſe, God
<pb facs="tcp:7109:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>procureth the ſaluation of his people,<note place="margin">God procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Croſſe.</note> vſing it as an inſtrument and help fit for the adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of regeneration begun in them, both to beate downe the fooliſhe &amp; vaine confidence of the fleſh, and to breake in pieces the veile of hypocriſie, which is naturally in it, and alſo to bridle his intemperancie. For the whole nature of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo prone to boaſt it ſelf proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and preſumptuouſly of his vertue &amp; ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie, that it is needefull to ſhewe him his frailetie, as it were with the finger &amp; before his eyes, to the ende he may be humbled and brought to a more true &amp; certain knowledge of him ſelf by a liuely feeling of his feblenes, and learne to cal for ſtrength from the Lord, as Jonas did,<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of man with the ſea</note> ſaying, I remembred the Lord when my ſoule was in anguiſhe: &amp; Dauid, when I was in tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I cried to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord: for it fareth ſo with men, as it doeth with the ſea, which would be infected and ſtinke, if it were not troubled with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> windes: ſo would men be naught, if they were not ſometimes toſſed with afflictions.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The croſſe ſerueth for a certaintie of our electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>And therefore as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worldly croſſe ſerueth the world for a witnes of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation, ſo this croſſe being ſanctified is an aſſurance and certaintie to the elect of their election, adoption, &amp; felowſhip they haue with Chriſt, the reſt of his afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s being acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed in
<pb facs="tcp:7109:60"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hers &amp; parte of him. For as Chriſt ſuffred once in himſelf,<note place="margin">Ieſus Chriſt ſuffreth in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers.</note> ſo ſuffreth he daily in his members, as the head ſuffreth with the parts of the bodie. And ſo his members are made like to him by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame tryal of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, with ſuch a grace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moreouer &amp; beſide they are quit &amp; exempt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe paines which all men deſerue generally for their ſinnes, they are honorably marked with the markes and badges of his ſonne, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Father appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted they ſhould be afflicted for his name. And wheras he might by good reaſon haue made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffer more grieuouſly, yea as ſhamefull thieues, murderers, robbers, &amp; euil doers, he maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffer as innocents laying vpon them the perſone of his ſonne, and cauſeth them to ſuffer for his ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">God taketh no pleaſure in the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of his, but chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them for their profite.</note>And though notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding al this, they be ſubiect to al miſeries which al men taſt of indifferently, both good and euil, yea &amp; worſe puniſhed then other, in ſo much that if a man would compare their afflictions with other mens, a man would thinke there were none ſo bad as they: &amp; that God doeth (as a man would ſay) ſpare the wicked, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of his rigour which he ſheweth toward his: yet we may not thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God taketh a pleaſure in their torments, &amp; as ſome prophane men
<pb facs="tcp:7109:61"/>ſay, that he maketh but a ſport &amp; paſtime of it when he ſo afflicteth men, hauing caſt of the care &amp; prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of mens affaires. But on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie ſide, becauſe God iudgeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world a right, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man can eſcape his hands with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out puniſhment, he moderateth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſeth his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in ſuch ſort, that he winketh at many lewde turnes which the wicked co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, as though he ſawe them not, and in the meane ſeaſon correcteth his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſone as they make a fault, &amp; the reaſon is, becauſe he hath a care of them to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the right way, purpoſing to make his prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce eſpecially knowen in the gouernement of his Church, and ſo vſeth his arme towardes it, that by the waye he giueth vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, he hath a fatherly care of vs, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth for the ſaluation of his Church.</p>
               <p>And truely if amongeſt men there be no father, of ſounde and right iudgement, but will chaſtice his children, becauſe without correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is not able to bring them to any good point: howe ſhall God, who is a moſt gracious &amp; wiſe father, forſlacke a remedie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſo neceſſarie? Which notwithſtanding he vſeth inſuch ſort, that whereas he puniſheth and iudgeth the world, and ſheweth him ſelf a ſeuere &amp; angrie iudge againſt the froward,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:61"/>he ſheweth him ſelf gracious and gentle to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his. For by this meanes, he meaneth to giue al men ſome litle taſte of that which he wil ſhew playnely in the latter day, to wit, that he is the iudge of the world, and loueth iuſtice in deede, and hateth vniuſtice deadly, both to make the vnbeleuers ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more inexcuſable, and alſo for the great profit and commoditie of the faithful, to whom he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth, that he doeth not puniſh them for any hatred he beareth them, but contrariwyſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loueth them, to amende them by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions which are the fruites of ſinne, and cauſe them to runne more feruently to his grace, hauing once felt in the croſſe what the anger of God is, ſo that whereas the wicked are ouerwhelmed with the fearful torments which they ſuffer, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtian by being made partaker of the ſanctification of Chriſt, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the croſſe, hath an entrance into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyes of heauen, and euerlaſting life with him.</p>
               <p>And by this way it is, that God wil proue euery mans fayth,<note place="margin">The profe of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian by the Croſſe.</note> whether it be buylt vpon a ſure rocke or no, whether the ſeede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word be fallen vpon good ground, &amp; whether the doctrine of the Goſpell whiche men haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, be golde, ſiluer, and precious ſtones, or whether it be hay &amp; ſtubble, which the fire
<pb facs="tcp:7109:62"/>of tribulation conſumeth and bringeth to naught. For if we make ſo great accompt of golde which is but a metal, that we wil trye it in the fyer, to make it pleaſe vs the better, what marueill is there, if God trye the faith of his children after the ſame ſort, to the end that when we are once wel purged from the dregges and filthe of incredulitie whiche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth in vs, and are purified in the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of diuers afflictions, and ſo melted as it were a new, our faith may be of like accompt before him.</p>
               <p>And ſurely it wil be as eaſie to knowe a Chriſtian from an hypocrite by this tryal of affliction, as it is to know a piece of gold fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a piece of braſſe, when they come both to the anuile, and to be ſtriken with the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer: for braſſe wil not be handled, but when it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the beating, it breaketh, and maketh a ſharpe dinne and irkeſome: and gold ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſweetely, &amp; is plyable, you may ſtretch it out both in length and breadth in thinne and fine leaues as you liſt: euen ſo when an hypocrite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth betwene the anuile &amp; the hammer of affliction,<note place="margin">The Croſſe diſcouereth the falſe Chriſtian.</note> he braſteth with impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, he murmureth, cryeth out, and lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in blaſphemies againſt God: whereas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praiſeth God, giueth him thanks,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:62"/>and layeth out his heart, ſubmitting him ſelf willingly vnder the lords hand that ſtriketh him. Againe, by this exerciſe, God exerciſeth the faithfull to contemne this life,<note place="margin">The profite of the croſſe</note> &amp; ſtirreth them vp, to thinke vpon and deſire the life to come, by drawing them away by litle &amp; litle, from the fooliſh and immoderat loue of this world, daſeled with a vayne ſhew of fleſhly &amp; tranſitorie things: and moreouer to ioyne them togither with his ſonne in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> felowſhip of the croſſe, that as he paſſed through a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit of miſeries to enter into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly glorie, ſo ſhould they alſo come thither by diuers tribulations, herein honouring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in making them ſuffer perſecution for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes ſake, that is to ſay, for the defenſe of his trueth agaynſt the lyes of Satan, or to mainteine al iuſt cauſes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei may be in like ſort renowmed as his ſonne was here in this world, and through more ſufferance of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries wherein he maketh his gifts and graces appeare which he beſtowed vpon them, be ſo much the more confirmed in that felowſhip which they haue with him, to the ende they may be notorious for his glorie, and profit of his Church, which is by this meanes obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently gouerned.</p>
               <p>But the chiefeſt thing that is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb facs="tcp:7109:63"/>in this point, &amp; is in deed the choyſeſt piece of Excellencie that is to be founde in a Chriſtian y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuffreth for Chriſts ſake,<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of a Chriſtian man appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnder the croſſe.</note> is this, that where al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are naturally afrayd, &amp; are ſad and penſiue when any aduerſities befall them, murmure againſt God, curſe their life, &amp; fal out to banning againſt heauen &amp; earth, deteſting their ſtate as miſerable, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian very quietly &amp; contentedly beareth pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently whatſoeuer befalleth him, not that he is ſo voyd of ſenſe, that he feeleth no grief, or affliction were not ſharpe &amp; irkſome to him, and very harde to beare, (for if it were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, how could he be pacient if he feele no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) but becauſe the croſſe of Chriſt hath this propertie, that being accompanied with the vertue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt, which ſweteneth the ſharpenes &amp; bitternes of all afflictions, it engendreth peace and meekenes in the heart of the Chriſtian, and alſo thankes giuing, for a ſingular benefit receyued of God, &amp; cauſeth him euen in the middes of the greateſt cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities &amp; griefs that may come vpon him, to haue a ioyful and mery heart, and receine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for an eſpecial cauſe of comfort. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe two affections, whiche are ioye and ſadnes, great enemies the one to the other, come &amp; mete ſo togither, that the one is conſtrained
<pb facs="tcp:7109:63"/>to giue place to the other, as the ſtronger &amp; hauing the vpper hande: in ſo much that the ioy of the ſpirit which is incomprehenſible, &amp; as S. Paul ſayeth, inexplicable, in that that it proceedeth from a taſte of heauenly giftes, doeth in fine ſwalowe vp as it were y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and heauines. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrarie ſide, they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue no taſte of thoſe giftes, can not chuſe but at length be oppreſſed with ſadnes, when aduerſitie aſſayleth them, for ſo much as the ſweete &amp; louing yoke of Chriſt is to heauy a burden for them, becauſe they can not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, how God our moſt louing and mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Father giueth them power to ſuffer that which they doo ſuffer, to bring them to his bliſſe, wheras the Chriſtian mounteth vp on high, and paſſeth the very heauens, &amp; holdeth him ſelf quiet and glad for the bliſſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance to come, as though he had it in his boſome, committing himſelfe for the reſt to Gods direction &amp; gouernement, as in deede it belongeth to the Father, who is of right aboue al fathers. And ſo not meaſuring the puniſhments after the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the fleſh, but giuing honour to God, he acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he moderateth his puniſhments both diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretely &amp; wiſely, ſo that there can be nothing found in them, but very good moderation, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7109:64"/>ſuch meaſure, that though through weaknes of reaſon he be not alwayes able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende it, yet he hath ſufficient to comfort him ſelfe, in that he knoweth that Gods indge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are moſt iuſt and righteous.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> paſſeth through a ſtrong flood or ſtreame on foote,<note place="margin">A fit compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſon of the Chriſtian paſſing tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the miſeries of this world.</note> leſt he ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and fal downe, ſetteth his eie ſtedily vpon the firme lande which he mindeth to atteine vnto, &amp; marketh not the ſwift courſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; ſo goeth ouer ſafely and is nothing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed: ſo this man paſſing through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raging waues of preſent troubles, turneth away his ſight, his thought, &amp; all apprehenſion that he might otherwiſe haue of the miſerie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and lifting vp his eyes to heauen, beholdeth there with a ſpiritual regard the ineſtimable treaſures of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenly inheritance, which he ſtriueth to atteine vnto, &amp; by this meanes ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely ſurmounteth al horrour and feare of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; griefs which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly make altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in mens heads, &amp; caſteth them hedlong into deſperation. So then he ſtandeth ſurely ſetled,<note place="margin">The glorie of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an in the Croſſe.</note> &amp; marcheth on without feare, &amp; not ſo only but leapeth for ioy, &amp; reioyceth in his tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, &amp; glorieth in the croſſe, which the world accompteth ſhamefull &amp; infamous, as in a thing which he eſtemeth moſt precious
<pb facs="tcp:7109:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>and honourable, &amp; more full of maieſtie then al the crownes &amp; ſcepters, proude pompes &amp; triumphes of al the Kings in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world wondereth at: for he caſteth his eies vpon Ieſus Chriſt, and beholdeth in him the glorie of his ſuffera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, wherby he ſeeth him ſelf glorified with him, and the reproche that commeth by him to become nothing. And in deede, who is he that wil accompt that thing ignominious which is holy, yea &amp; ſanctified of God: Or who would deſpiſe that, wherby the children of God are prepared to glorie, which is ſo farre from being diminiſhed in a Chriſtian, through the contemptible ſtate of this preſent life, that it is rather augmented: And Moſes for this cauſe thought the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which he ſuffred for Chriſts ſake, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter richeſſe, then all the treaſures of Egypt.</p>
               <p>The croſſe of Antichriſt &amp; of his members hath nothing like, it is harde,<note place="margin">The croſſe of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</note> grieuous and ſhameful to beare. For in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſeeke not to be iuſtified by Chriſt, they labour in vaine by going about to iuſtifie them ſelues, &amp; ſhewe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be enemies to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe of Chriſt, ſtriuing to beare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mortification of the croſſe by many fooliſh inuentions, &amp; withdrawing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into deſert &amp; incloſed places, vnpro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitably puniſhing their bodies without faith,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:65"/>w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out Chriſt, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out hope, &amp; without charitie.</p>
               <p>Thus the Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> findeth combes of hony in the Lyons belly,<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of a Chriſtian in affliction.</note> that is to ſaye, ioye, gladnes and glorie, in the deepeſt &amp; greateſt miſeries that may be, and a quiet ſtate in the gulfe of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtes, as if he were in full bliſſe, &amp; already rayſed vp from death to lyfe, &amp; ſet in the heauenly places with Ieſus Chriſt, in whom he poſſeſſeth euen from this inſtant e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting glorie &amp; bliſſe, and obteineth vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie againſt the rage of Satan, &amp; al the force the world is able to vſe: for to him it is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to treade the Lyons vnder foote, &amp; alſo the dragons, and al other hurtful power, becauſe he marcheth vnder the enſeigne of this vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant captaine which wil neuer loſe any one of his, though he employ them &amp; exerciſe them in continuall combats, giuing them this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie, that who ſo continueth ſtedfaſt &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in attayning to the glory of his hope, ſhal in the end obteine a good and bleſſed end, whereas the man that is afraid to make head and ſet him ſelf courageouſly againſt al that exalteth it ſelf as enemie againſt God, is not able to ſay that he hath a true hope in him.</p>
               <p>And though the trueth be ſo, that there is not a weaker creature in the world then ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, ſubiect to the world, the fleſh, &amp; the deuill,
<pb facs="tcp:7109:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>and al his luſtes, (though he had all the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> and ſtrength of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> and vertue of the Philoſophers, and righteouſnes of the Iewes in him) alwayes in feare, care, and horrour, and one that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not reſiſt the leſt tentation that may befal him: For he is but a ſhadow of vanitie, yea &amp; vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie it ſelf: yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding being regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in Ieſus Chriſt, he is ſo ſtrong &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that though he caſt of all worldly helpe &amp; fauour, as Dauid put of his armour when he went to fight againſt <hi>Goliath,</hi> he doeth not only reſiſt al aſſaults of the world, fleſh, &amp; the deuil valiantly, but alſo ſurmounteth all the enemies of God by the vertue of faith, which cauſeth vs to ſee by her light y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all creatures are but fanſies and vaine fearebabes, which haue no power, but as pleaſeth God to giue them, whom we acknowledge to be our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath ſuch a ſingular &amp; fatherly care of vs, that he maketh al things ſerue to our ſaluation: euen ſo much that this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tranſformed into God by loue which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth al things, can no more be ouercome the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God him ſelf, being ſure in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, at quiet in torment, in pouertie riche, in ſicknés whole, quiet in perſecution, glorious in ignominie, bleſſed in miſerie, aliue in death, &amp; therefore victorious and triumphant ouer all his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies:
<pb facs="tcp:7109:66"/>for he that is borne of God, ſaieth S. Iohn, ouercommeth the world.</p>
               <p>Hereby we may gather, how falſly thei brag &amp; boaſt of them ſelues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are Chriſtians,<note place="margin">He that would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt him ſelfe from the croſſe, abuſeth the name of a Chriſtian.</note> which wil nedes be exempt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of the Chriſtians, as thogh it were poſſible to lay ſuch hold vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſt as we ought, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might embrace him, &amp; let his croſſe go: and as though we might be members of his bodie, and not be partakers of his ſuffera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, which is but a mere &amp; vaine imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence, that we do not ſo rightly iudge of the benefit of adoption as we ought to do, but caſt away the grace, which ſanctifieth vs to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth is ſo, that who ſo profeſſeth him ſelf to be a chriſtian &amp; is aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to folow Chriſt who goeth before him, doeth nothing els but cut of him ſelf, as you would ſay, &amp; diſauoweth him ſelf to be any of Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the Goſpel is neuer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither is there any way to come to the kingdome of heauen, but by the croſſe, though a man would neuer ſo much flatter &amp; excuſe himſelf, vnder a colour of weakenes, which is nothing els, to ſpeake as the trueth is in dede, but infidelitie, &amp; a ſmall accompt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man maketh of the holy &amp; ſacred name of the Sonne of God. For certaine it is that faith ſhal alwayes ouercome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, but that can
<pb facs="tcp:7109:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>not be done without fight. And he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for feare to confeſſe Gods name openly, alleageth for him ſelf, that yet notwithſtanding God ſeeth his heart, ſayeth trew, becauſe he can ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in him but infidelitie &amp; hypocriſie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing nothing, to ſay the trueth, to turne him away from Chriſt, but only becauſe he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with his croſſe, diſfigured &amp; contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſubiect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reproches of this world, &amp; calleth vs to be partakers of his afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. So that this kinde of men preferreth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of this world, before the glorie &amp; maieſtie of Chriſt which is ſpiritual, and the eaſe and quietnes of this life before euerlaſting bliſſe: playing therein y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> part of <hi>Eſops</hi> cocke, which found a riche &amp; precious pearle, &amp; forſoke it for a graine of corne, ſo vile and abiect &amp; baſe their heart is, voyd of al noblenes &amp; courage of a Chriſtian heart, which ſurmoneth al vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible things, as one of the houſholde of God, yea his chyld &amp; heire, being aſſured that there is a better poſſeſſion in heauen, then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which men ſeeke here vpon earth. But ſeeing the world is ſo brutiſhe, &amp; ful of malice and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, we nede not merueile, if we ſee the moſt part of men draw back &amp; cowardly caſt away their weapons, as ſoone as they ſee the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dart of the croſſe ſet vp, as we haue ſene more examples then were to be wiſhed: and that of
<pb facs="tcp:7109:67"/>ſuch as at the beginning ſeemed to be vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ſoldiers, which had neuer learned to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and fight againſt their enemies but with a certaine hautines of courage, which paſſeth away by and by, &amp; not to poſſeſſe their ſoules in patience. Theſe and ſuch like are the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant markes &amp; ſignes of the holy Ghoſt in a Chriſtian man, and his true ornaments &amp; beautie that hath put on Ieſus Chriſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may be knowen from other.</p>
               <p>Now that we haue in this ſorte ſpoken of the Excellencie of this man,<note place="margin">A man is to be taken for a Chriſtian, though he haue not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned to a perfection.</note> by marking and ſetting him forth in his colours, no man may thinke that I wil take no man for a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, but him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath theſe markes ſo perfectly as though he were ful of the holy Ghoſt, and renewed with ſuche vprightnes of lyfe, as though he wanted nothing. For if the caſe ſtoode ſo, it were very hard to finde any ſuch amongſt men, for there hath neuer bin man yet ſo perfect. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſpeake of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, as of a man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is truly renewed, &amp; made ſpiritual, iuſt &amp; without blame, we may not thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worke of this making a new creature, is a work done in a moment, or in a day,<note place="margin">The worke of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not perfited in one day.</note> yea or perfected all this lyfe long: as we may not alſo thinke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is a worke which is wrought equally in al: for it is a work which God furdereth in proces of time by litle and
<pb facs="tcp:7109:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>litle, &amp; as it were by degrees, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaſure that it pleaſeth him to giue to eche of vs, vntil he haue brought it to perfection.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How a Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian man is ſaid to be ſpiritual and righteous.</note>So that the ſpirit of God which is giuen to a Chriſtian, doeth ſo aboliſhe the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the fleſh, that there remaine notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding euen to death certaine reliques of the old man, but yet ſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end getteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpper hand: For it can not be, but he is the ſtrongeſt wherſoeuer he is, &amp; by the efficacie of his mouing, he holdeth men neceſſarily in ſtedy and continual obedience of Iuſtice, as the ſeede wherby he is regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, is incorruptible. By meanes whereof, though this man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſo regenerate, abideth notwithſtanding in the fleſh, and ſinne dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in him: yet according to his better part, and in reſpect of the ſpirit that in the end ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in him, he is called ſpiritual, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> though there be at this preſent no ſuch perfection in the world, but there may be ſome fault found with it, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he is already cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, as it were, inreprehenſible, &amp; without blame, who is regenerate &amp; of a right heart tendeth to this marke. And I thought good to adde this point, to the end that no man ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage him ſelfe, though he feele not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect regeneration and crucifying of the fleſh in him ſelf, and a ful and whole quickening of
<pb facs="tcp:7109:68"/>the ſpirit, but lay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> before him which I ſpake of before, as it were a patern wherby he hath to forme &amp; frame his life, ſhooting alwayes at the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as at a marke which he muſt alwaies leuel at, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering how ſmal a thing it is and of litle accompt to enter into the liſt of the Goſpel, vnleſſe we labour and ſtriue to come to the end. for the chiefeſt wiſdome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt, is to draw on further, and to go on more and more, as the calling of a Chriſtian man requireth: nay no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to thinke of him ſelf that he hath profited but ſmally, that can feele in him ſelf ſome ſigne &amp; witnes of that felowſhip he hath with Chriſt in his death, &amp; reſurrection through new motions of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feined heart, which ſtriueth in dede to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life. Conſidering that God of his free goodnes vouchſaueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holy affection which he him ſelf planteth in the heartes of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants this honour, that he taketh him for a Chriſtian, which is not ſo as yet properly: for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not come to this happines in this life to be cleane from all ſinne, and to haue a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of faith &amp; pure charitie. And in that that a man is taken to be a Chriſtian, it is by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the newnes of life that is begonne in him through the vertue of the holy Ghoſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by his vertue quickeneth him, vntil he be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectly renewed: which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be done before
<pb facs="tcp:7109:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>the time that we ſhal haue put of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mortalitie of theſe our bodies, and therewithall, the filth of ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, that he ſhould wel examine himſelf whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther he be truely a Chriſtian.</note>And therfore let a man examine his life, &amp; ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his heart to the depth, to know whether he finde the markes of a Chriſtian there or no: and in caſe he do finde them there, let him be as thankeful to God as if he had receiued the greateſt benefit in the world, being aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that his name is written in heauen. And therfore let him with <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſkip for ioye, &amp; crie out with <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> &amp; enlarge his to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue with <hi>Zacharie,</hi> and magnifie the Lord with the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> for that it hath pleaſed him to caſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, being but a worme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eies of his great mercy, to make him taſte ſuch high things, ſo riche &amp; ſecret to the ſenſe of man, that there is no eye can ſee them, no eare can heare them, nor heart and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend them. And let that man know, that this ſecret was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, to the end he ſhould keepe this ſo great a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit vnto death, by encreaſing the ſame faithe, whereby he was receiued to be partaker of this benefit: for it is the ende of a Chriſtian mans calling to go on more &amp; more in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Godward, &amp; to ſtriue without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to draw euery day more nere then other to him, regarding on the one ſide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes
<pb facs="tcp:7109:69"/>of God on them that continue, &amp; on the other ſide his ſeueritie on them, which abuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; bountifulnes of his grace. And if on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide he can not know in him ſelfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is a Chriſtian choſen of God, let him ſobbe &amp; ſighe before his face, &amp; pray to him to make him partaker of his light &amp; heauenly grace, to the end he may be out of doubt. for he that doubteth, hath not as yet ſufficient light in him, ſeeing the efficacie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> witnes of Gods ſpirit is ſo cleare and certaine in his heart in whom he is,<note place="margin">That man is very blind y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade him ſelf he is a Chriſtian.</note> that as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> point, there is no doubt. But we may well ſay that that man is blinde, peruers, &amp; miſerable, that can not perſuade himſelf ſo much of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes, mightie power &amp; trueth of God, as to beleue his promiſes which he hath made, &amp; ſworne, and pronounced ſo ſolemnely. And therefore let euery man ſtriue with him ſelfe to make his election ſure through a good conſcience, and ſinceritie of life anſwerable to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his faith, &amp; labour by al meanes poſſible, that the world may know in deede that it is not in baine that he perſuadeth himſelf, he is a Chriſtian.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
